<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>New experiments, and observations, made upon the icy noctiluca imparted in a letter to a friend living in the country : to which is annexed A chymical paradox / by Robert Boyle.</title>
            <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3995</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13447</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11704469</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11704469</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48263</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29000)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48263)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 483:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>New experiments, and observations, made upon the icy noctiluca imparted in a letter to a friend living in the country : to which is annexed A chymical paradox / by Robert Boyle.</title>
                  <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 150 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.E. for B. Tooke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681/2.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A chymical paradox" has special t.p. and is paged continuously.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Phosphorus.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48263:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NEW EXPERIMENTS, AND OBSERVATIONS, Made upon the ICY NOCTILUCA.</p>
            <p>Imparted in a Letter to a Friend living in the Country.</p>
            <p>To which is annexed A Chymical Paradox.</p>
            <p>By the Honourable <hi>ROBERT BOYLE,</hi> Fellow of the <hi>Royal Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. E.</hi> for <hi>B. Tooke,</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1681/2.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:48263:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:48263:2"/>
                  <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT OF THE PUBLISHER TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>THoſe, who have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed ſome former Tracts of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Author's, have made their Complaints, That his Writings have not met with the ſame Candor and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity from all Writers: For
<pb facs="tcp:48263:3"/> though <hi>ſome</hi> have very civilly mentioned his Name in thoſe Experiments, Obſervations, and <hi>Phaenomena,</hi> which they have borrowed from His Writings; yet <hi>others</hi> have vendicated that to themſelves, which was none of their own; for having light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Candle at his Torch, and raiſed ſome Superſtructures upon thoſe Foundations he had laid, they have made no menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him at all; in which mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Sincerity of Philoſophers is not a little required.</p>
                  <p>'Tis known, That Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> was the Firſt Inventer of that <hi>Pneuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> Engine, or <hi>Air-Pump,</hi> called from Him, <hi>Machina Boiliana;</hi> the Figure and many of the uſes whereof he hath deſcribed in
<pb facs="tcp:48263:3"/> his <hi>Tract</hi> entituled, <hi>New Phyſico-Mechanical Experiments concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Spring and Weight of the Air,</hi> (and in the <hi>Continuation</hi> of it;) which Book, being Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into <hi>Latin,</hi> and diſperſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Forreign Parts, hath given oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to Tranſmarine <hi>Virtuoſi</hi> to make Eſſays (not altogether unſucceſsful) concerning the Fabricating of the like Engines; though none of their Tracts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Subject have equall'd the Original. In like manner 'tis highly probable that his Diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations concerning <hi>Phoſphorus</hi>'s, and his free Diſtribution of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Parcels of that <hi>Luminous Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> have excited others to deſcant upon the ſame <hi>Subject.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But that it may juſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear,
<pb facs="tcp:48263:4"/> That the Honourable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſhines only by his own Light, and hath not any thing mutuatitious in the following <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> the Reader is to be adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, That this Tract had much earlier come abroad, if, after I had received the <hi>Whole,</hi> even to the laſt Sheet in 1681. that ſo the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Edition, and my <hi>Latin</hi> Verſion thereof (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Noble <hi>Author</hi> was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to gratifie the <hi>Curious</hi> in Forreign Parts) might be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on together, I had not been by long Sickneſs, and divers unfavourable and unexpected <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ircumſtances, obliged to retain it ſome Months in my Hands.</p>
                  <p>Which I am the more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d at, becauſe I find, that my
<pb facs="tcp:48263:4"/> neceſſitated Delay hath given Opportunity to the Publication of ſome Experiments about <hi>Noctiluca</hi>'s. But the <hi>Virtuoſi,</hi> who have the Honour to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Noble Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Book, and have ſeen the laſt <hi>Summer</hi> and <hi>Autumn</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the Chief Experiments made, which are mentioned therein, will eaſily believe, that the Author needed not to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row any thing from thoſe <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimens</hi> which have been late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publiſhed by an ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Man about <hi>Noctiluca</hi>'s; which, beſide that they contain but very few <hi>Phaenomena,</hi> or <hi>Trials</hi> coincident with <hi>His,</hi> were ſo far from affording him any Information, that (to be
<pb facs="tcp:48263:5"/> ſure to be no Borrower) he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver would to this day read any one of them, or hear them read. And it appears, by the Cloſe of the <hi>Aerial Noctiluca,</hi> preſented in Print to the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end of the Year 1680. that he then knew and had pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticed ſeveral other Ways of making <hi>Noctiluca</hi>'s, than <hi>That,</hi> which he <hi>Then,</hi> and before any other Man, imparted to the World.</p>
                  <p>The Uſefulneſs of the enſuing Diſcoveries and Reflexions will be beſt judg'd of by diſcerning Readers, who therefore need not to be previouſly informed thereof by me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:48263:5"/>
                  <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe very kind Recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you were pleaſed to give thoſe Papers about the <hi>AERIAL NOCTILUCA,</hi> that I addreſs'd to you about the beginning of the laſt Winter, does not only invite me, but in a manner oblige me to impart to you ſome Trials, that I made, after I had ſent you the others, about the ſame kind of <hi>Phoſphorus;</hi> to which you may now be pleas'd to annex them, by way of Continuation, or Appendix. But that being true, which is noted
<pb facs="tcp:48263:6"/> by <hi>Lucretius,</hi> where he prettily ſays, That—<hi>Res accendunt lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina rebus,</hi> you will not think it ſtrange, that if this Obſervation holds in other things, it ſhould particularly take place in Lumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous things themſelves: and therefore, without any further Preamble, I ſhall tell you, That whilſt my Occaſions permitted me to ſtay in <hi>London,</hi> I was willing to try, whether I could carry on ſomewhat further that which had already been not unſucceſsfully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun. And accordingly I caus'd to be prepar'd and diſtill'd four or five ſeveral Materials, which I thought the Curious, eſpecially thoſe addicted to Chymiſtry, would wiſh to have had Trials made upon, and would perhaps blame
<pb facs="tcp:48263:6"/> me, if I had omitted to employ. But thoſe Materials, not anſwering what was deſired, we made choice of another or two, which I forbear to name, for certain Reaſons, and particularly for this, becauſe they are to be found but in very few Places, and perhaps would not have ſerv'd my turn, if I had not luckily procur'd them in a Seaſon whoſe Dryneſs continued almoſt to a Wonder.</p>
                  <p>From theſe Materials ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and ſometimes alſo from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Reſidence of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine, we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow and then ſome of the <hi>Aerial Noctiluca,</hi> ſuch as That you have hitherto receiv'd Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of; but more frequently a Nobler ſort of <hi>Phoſphorus,</hi> about which I now proceed to impart to
<pb facs="tcp:48263:7"/> you ſome Obſervations, as I did, without any curious Method or Ornament, ſet them down from time to time as I hapned to make or remember them. And, to faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate the Pardon <hi>I</hi> beg of you, for having omitted ſome Experiments that perhaps you will wiſh <hi>I</hi> had made, <hi>I</hi> muſt acquaint you, That being by ſome Neceſſary Occaſions enforced to leave <hi>London,</hi> for a much longer time than <hi>I</hi> have done for ſeveral Years laſt paſt, <hi>I</hi> have been oblig'd to make moſt of the following Trials in a ſmall Village, where <hi>I</hi> yet am, and where, being unaccommodated with Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces, Inſtruments, and other Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical and Mechanical Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, for making and varying Experiments, you receive an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb facs="tcp:48263:7"/> not of all the Trials, <hi>I</hi> would have made, (ſome of the Chief of my Catalogue remaining ſtill un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>attempted) but of all Thoſe <hi>I</hi> could make in my preſent Circumſtances. However, ſuch as they are, <hi>I</hi> think not fit to delay any longer the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting you with them; and therefore have order'd them to be gather'd into one ſmall Collection of <hi>Memoirs,</hi> to which Paper <hi>I</hi> have given the Title of <hi>The Gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial or Icy Noctiluca,</hi> not only to diſtinguiſh it from the <hi>Aerial</hi> one, whereof you have already had an Account; but for another Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that you will quickly meet with in the little Tract it ſelf, from whoſe Peruſal <hi>I</hi> muſt not now any longer detain you.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:48263:8"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48263:8"/>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>An APPENDIX To the AERIAL NOCTILUCA.</head>
                     <div n="1" type="section">
                        <head>
                           <hi>SECT.</hi> I.</head>
                        <p>THE ſhining Matter, contain'd in our beſt Phials, being partly waſted in Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and partly given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, I thought fit to try, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the help of Heat and other Motion, our want might not be ſomewhat ſupplied, till more <hi>Nocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucous</hi> Matter could be prepared.</p>
                        <div n="1" type="experiment">
                           <pb n="2" facs="tcp:48263:9"/>
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> I.</head>
                           <p>In purſuit of this Deſign, I took an old Phial that had been long laid aſide as uſeleſs, becauſe the Matter had been poured out of it into a clearer and ſmaller Glaſs, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving held that ſide of this Phial, to which I perceived ſome Feculent Matter ſtuck, near the Fire, till it had conceived a conſiderable degree of warmth, I remov'd it into a dark place, and as I expected, found it to ſhine, and that Vividly enough, whilſt it retain'd a Competent degree of heat; and when it cooled too much, the Light ceaſed with the Agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that as a Cauſe or a Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on accompanied it. But if after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Phial were again held to the Fire as before, the ſhining Power would be excited, and the Splendor would continue a pretty while. But after ſome days or weeks (for I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not which,) this Diſpoſition to be made Luminous by external heat, was utterly loſt.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="experiment">
                           <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48263:9"/>
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> II.</head>
                           <p>Having alſo taken notice of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Feculent Stuff, that ſtuck to the inſide of the Glaſs, that had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd ſome of our <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter, I imagined, that though it would not ſhine in the dark by the contact of the Air, to which it had been too long accuſtomed; yet when once that diſpirited or diſanimated Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies, (if I may ſo call it,) that had lain expoſed to the Air, was removed, the more Internal part of the Matter might not be deſtitute of a ſhining Power. I carefully ſcraped off, the outermoſt Surface, and rubbing a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the reſt with my finger upon my hand, I found it to ſhine well enough. And though the Matter, being once more left expoſed to the Air, did loſe in its Superficial parts the Virtue of ſhining in the dark; yet thoſe parts being taken off, the remaining Matter (being rubb'd) did not appear deſtitute of a Luminous
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48263:10"/> Quality, ſo that it ſeemed, that though the Air did after a while, mortifie as it were and ſpoil the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficial parts that were expoſed to its immediate Contact, yet this vitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Surface ſerved for a kind of Cover or Fence to the Matter that lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath it, and kept it from Evapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating or Spending thoſe Spirituous or Subtile parts, on whoſe Account it was capable of becoming Luminous.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> III.</head>
                           <p>And as I had obſerved on other occaſions, that Liquors abounding in Tenacious parts, though the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors did not appear opacous or Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culent, would leave ſticking to the inſides of the Glaſſes, that contained them, ſomewhat, that though gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally not perceived, becauſe not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry manifeſt, was by ſome other ways that I had tried diſcoverable: Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, as I was ſaying, obſerv'd this, in ſome other Caſes, I ſuſpected, that even in a Phial that had formerly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48263:10"/> contained ſome of our ſhining Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, though it ſeemed to have been well emptied, and to have no groſs Feculency adhering to it, there might ſtick ſomewhat, which though unobſerved by the naked Eye, might be made viſible to the naked Eye, by heat or motion. In purſuance of this Conjecture, I took this Glaſs, and having crackt it into Fragments, that it might be put into the neck of a Phial of a convenient ſhape and ſize; and having well ſtopt the Veſſel and removed it into a dark place, we there ſhook it, and had the pleaſure to ſee, not only that Light was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily produced by the motion excited in the juſtling of the parts one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, but that by reaſon of the various poſition of the Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Glaſs, ſome looking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, ſome downwards, ſome to the right hand, and ſome to the left, the light ſeemed to be Vibrated every way, with a very delightful Vividneſs. This Production of a kind of blazing Light was often repeated with theſe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48263:11"/> pieces of Glaſs, and if the Phial were heated, the effect ſeemed more quick and conſiderable: And (if I miſremember not,) by only warming the Phial, without ſhaking it, a Light would be produced.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="4" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> IV.</head>
                           <p>Afterwards having beaten ſome of the Glaſs into ſuch ſmall pieces as were capable of paſſing through the neck of a Glaſs-Egg with a flat bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, that it might ſtand upright of it ſelf, we Hermetically ſealed up the neck, to try whether by this hindring the included Matter from exhaling or tranſpiring, we could keep the beaten Glaſs always fit to exhibit the <hi>Phaenomenon;</hi> but we found not the event anſwer our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, for after no long time, we could no more produce any Light in our Sealed Veſſel, though an unlucky Accident happening in one of our laſt Tryal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>, keeps me from being ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied of the unpracticableneſs of the thing deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>gned.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="5" type="experiment">
                           <pb n="7" facs="tcp:48263:11"/>
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> V.</head>
                           <p>In the Printed Tract of the <hi>Aerial Noctiluca,</hi> there is mention made of ſome Liquor that was <hi>Hermetically</hi> Sealed up in a bolt-Glaſs, that was not great, to try whether by this way we could for any long time preſerve the ſhining faculty of that Liquor wherein it was already ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding faint, and not to be excited but by a conſiderable degree of heat, and a vehement agitation of the Veſſel it ſelf. This Sealed Glaſs having been left in the corner of a Window, for what was judg'd a competent time, we yeſternight approached the Veſſel by degrees to the Fire, and ſhaking it from time to time till the inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Liquor had acquired a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable degree of heat. Then remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it to a dark place, and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Veſſel ſomewhat ſtrongly, we perceived that the diſpoſition the Liquor had to ſhine, was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much impaired, but not quite
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48263:12"/> aboliſhed. For there would from time to time, upon the rude agitation it was put into, appear lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle portions of Matter that looked prettily, and ſhone very Vividly, like ſparks of Fire; and ſome of theſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the <hi>Spherical</hi> part of the Glaſs, and ſome in the Neck. Some of them ſeemed as it were fixed to their firſt Station, and others moved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and downwards, and moſt of them continued ſome time to ſhine a pretty while before they diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and when they vaniſhed, few of them did ſo by degrees, but each luminous ſpeck, when it had laſted out its time, loſt its whole Light at once.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="section">
                        <head>
                           <hi>SECT.</hi> II.</head>
                        <p>THE new Liquid <hi>Phoſphorus,</hi> I lately mentioned to have been made, ſince the publiſhing of the <hi>Aeri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>l Noctiluca,</hi> was poured into a large Phial, that might contain (by our gueſs) ten or twelve times as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48263:12"/> much as was put into it, ſo that the ſhining Matter, having ſo much Air included with it, might thereby be aſſiſted to diverſifie at leaſt ſome of the <hi>Phenomena</hi> afforded by former <hi>Noctilucas.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <div n="1" type="observation">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Obſervation</hi> I.</head>
                           <p>And accordingly I obſerved in the firſt place, that though the ſhining ſteams filled the whole cavity of the large Glaſs, that was untaken up by the Liquor and the reſidence, and this lighter flame continued much longer at once, than any we have hitherto mentioned, for it continued Vivid ſeveral Days and Nights toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without ever unſtopping the Phial to give it freſh Air. And, if I miſremember not, I obſerv'd it to do ſo for about a week, before my occaſions hindred me from obſerving it any longer.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="observation">
                           <pb n="10" facs="tcp:48263:13"/>
                           <head>
                              <hi>Obſervation</hi> II.</head>
                           <p>I ſometimes took notice with pleaſure, that ſome Exhalations or Vapours, that appeared conſiderably luminous, ſeemed to roll to and fro, like little Clouds or Aggregates of Smoak in the Cavity of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, though it ſeemed difficult to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine what ſhould give them, and maintain in them, ſuch a motion.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="observation">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Obſervation</hi> III.</head>
                           <p>The bigneſs of the Glaſs being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, it happened that ſometimes when I went into the darkned place where I kept it, ſo much luminous Matter would make a ſurpriſing ſhow, but though its extent were far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet its intenſity did not much exceed that of the Light afforded by the <hi>Noctilucas</hi> of the firſt ſort, as for diſtinctions ſake, thoſe may be called that are mentioned in the Printed Account. Only this I often
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48263:13"/> took notice of, that, in caſe I ſhook the Matter gently, the Light would appear much more vivid. and, as it were, would flaſh in and about the ſurface of the Liquor where it was Contiguous to the Air, than it did elſewhere. And this ſplendor was ſuch, that if it had been laſting, I thought it would have made our <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> uſeful for conſiderable pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="4" type="observation">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Obſervation</hi> IV.</head>
                           <p>When after having ſo many Days kept this Glaſs ſtopt, at laſt it would not longer ſhine of it ſelf, we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it to be reduced to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> of the firſt ſort, and accordingly found, that upon the removal of the Stoppel, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of freſh Air, the Cavity would in a moment be filled with fumes that lookt white in an enlightned place, but luminous in a dark one, and (probably by reaſon of the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of the Air contain'd in ſo capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48263:14"/> a Glaſs) the light uſually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued much longer than 'twas wont to do in <hi>Noctilucas</hi> of the firſt ſort.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="5" type="observation">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Obſervation</hi> V.</head>
                           <p>Being deſirous to try, whether this more vigorous Matter, if it were kept ſo exactly ſtopped, that none of the Luminous Vapours could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hale, would not laſt very long, I put near two ſpoonfuls of the Liquor with ſome of the ſediment into a bolt-Glaſs (with a flat bottom that it might ſtand without leaning) ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of containing in all near twice as much, this Glaſs being Hermetically Sealed, the included Liquor continu'd to ſhine without any external help either of Air or Heat, for about ſix Days and Nights, but then it gave over ſhining, nor would be made lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous again by moderate ſhaking.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="6" type="observation">
                           <pb n="13" facs="tcp:48263:14"/>
                           <head>
                              <hi>Obſervation</hi> VI.</head>
                           <p>After having poured out ſome more of the Liquor and Sediment that had been kept in the great Phial, former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mentioned, into a ſmaller Phial, to make a Preſent of it to a <hi>Virtuoſo,</hi> the remaining Matter, having now a greater proportion of Air included with it, was very apt to be put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Luminous agitation, if I may ſo call it, and would emit Exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that would not only fill the Cavity of the Glaſs, but manifeſtly move to and fro in it after a ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what odd manner. And being one Night willing to give a Lady, and ſome other Company, the divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a new <hi>Phenomenon,</hi> after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving opened the Phial, and then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtopt it again, I ſhook it, and turned it in ſuch a way, that much the greateſt part of Liquor having been before poured out, the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence was as it were ſpread over the inſide of the Glaſs, to which its Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48263:15"/> ſtuck, becauſe there wanted Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor enough to waſh them down: By which means, thoſe little portions of the Sediment being not covered, as they were wont to be with Water, but expoſed to the immediate Contact of the Air, ſhone much more vivid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than the Luminous Exhalations were wont to do, and the light be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tremulous and twinkling, as well as brisk, they ſeemed to emulate ſo many little Stars in a Cloudleſs but dark Night, and continued this Scin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillation longer than one would have expected, to the no ſmall delight of the beholders, for whoſe ſake the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment was ſeveral times repeated with ſucceſs.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:48263:15"/>
                     <head>NEW PHAENOMENA Exhibited by an ICY NOCTILUCA, OR, Solid Self-ſhining Subſtance.</head>
                     <div n="3" type="section">
                        <head>
                           <hi>SECT.</hi> III.</head>
                        <p>IN the Addreſs of the foregoing Appendix to the <hi>Aerial Noctilu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> I intimated the Reaſon, why I did not think fit to give you a more particular account of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials I employ'd in proſecuting my deſign, of making better qualified <hi>Noctilucas.</hi> And therefore I ſhall not for the preſent trouble you with the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48263:16"/> mention of proceedings, that for want of ſome things ſeldom procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, you would not where you live, be able to imitate: But ſhall ſave you and my ſelf the trouble of a further preamble.</p>
                        <p>Having then by proceſſes, not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like that I annexed to the Cloſe of the <hi>Aerial Noctiluca,</hi> obtain'd a Self-ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Subſtance of a <hi>Conſiſtent form;</hi> I proceed to give you ſome account of what I have obſerved about it, and try'd with it, which will take up the leſs time to do, becauſe many things belonging to it in common with the ſhining Liquor, with which I have already entertain'd you, thoſe will be the fewer that belong pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly to the Self-ſhining Matter, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow'd with a <hi>Conſiſtent form.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>About which it may be proper to take notice of ſome affections, that ſeem more immediately to belong to the Subſtance it ſelf, than moſt of the things do that are to follow.</p>
                        <div type="part">
                           <pb n="17" facs="tcp:48263:16"/>
                           <head>Some Qualities of the <hi>Noctiluca</hi> it ſelf.</head>
                           <p n="1">1. And firſt, Though it uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly came over in diſtillation in the form of divers little Grains, or Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, differing for the moſt part from one another, both in bigneſs (ſome being of the ſize of Grains of Corn, and others of Peaſe, or large Cherry-Stones) and alſo as to their ſhapes, which moſt commonly were irregular, as Concretions are wont to be, that are caſually produced, yet when the Diſtillation was carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on proſperouſly, we obtain'd the deſired Matter in greater Lumps, ſometimes as large as ſmall Beans, and ſometimes at leaſt three or four times as large, but not proportionably thick.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. Theſe Lumps whether ſmall or great, were Colourleſs; and uſually when they were held againſt the Light, tranſparent; ſo that divers Bodies placed beyond them at a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient diſtance, might be plainly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48263:17"/> ſeen through them. And ſome of the bigger appeared ſo like ſuch Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Ice,</hi> as being thin, are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times very clear, and almoſt quite deſtitute of manifeſt Bubbles; that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of this great reſemblance, and for diſtinction ſake, I thought it not amiſs to call our conſiſtent Self-ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Subſtance, the <hi>Icy</hi> or <hi>Glacial Noctiluca</hi> (and for variety <hi>Phoſphorus</hi>) which name I choſe to give it, rather than that of <hi>Cryſtalline,</hi> becauſe this Epithet is not unfrequently given to every <hi>Diaphanous</hi> Liquor, as well as to <hi>Tranſparent</hi> Solids. But when I ſaid, that our <hi>Noctiluca</hi> was Tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and Colourleſs, I meant it only in reference to what uſually appeared. For whether it were any real diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the Texture or conſtitution of the Body it ſelf, or the effect of ſome caſual junctures of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, I am not ſure; but this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd to us, that ſometime, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Candle-Light, ſome leſſer Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments appeared not <hi>Diaphanous,</hi> nor always either Colourleſs, nor of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48263:17"/> ſame Colour. For ſometimes the Matter looked Reddiſh, ſometimes of a faint, but pleaſing Blew, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times too, of a Colour to which I cannot eaſily aſſign a known Name.</p>
                           <p n="3">3. Our <hi>Icy Noctiluca</hi> or <hi>Phoſphorus,</hi> is manifeſtly heavier in <hi>Specie</hi> than common Water, in which being put, it readily ſinks to the bottom, and quietly lies there.</p>
                           <p n="4">4 The Ice like Body, though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent, is not hard; being far leſs ſo, than common <hi>Ice;</hi> but yet 'tis not ſo ſoft but that 'tis brittle, and will more eaſily be broken in pieces by the preſſure of ones Fingers, than receive ſhapes from them; and yet by him that goes ſomewhat warily to work, it may be ſpread upon a ſolid Body, almoſt like the unmelted Tallow of a Candle.</p>
                           <p n="5">5. The Conſiſtent <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> is fuſible enough. For though in the Air it will not be brought to melt, without ſome difficulty and waſte, yet by the help of hot Liquors, and even of Water it ſelf, it may with a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48263:18"/> little care and dexterity be brought to melt, which is an Obſervation of good uſe; becauſe by means of fuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeveral Fragments (if the Matter be pure enough) may be brought to run into one Lump, and in that condition may both be the better preſerved, and become fit to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to ſome conſiderable uſes, which cannot ſo well, if at all, be made of leſſer, though numerous Fragments.</p>
                           <p n="6">6. This <hi>Glacial Noctiluca</hi> is, as to ſenſe, cold, but of a texture that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſes it to be eaſily agitated, and by agitation become incaleſcent, as will appear hereafter. When this Solid <hi>Noctiluca</hi> is held in the free Air, though perhaps its ſuperficies be wet, it affords a very vivid Light, uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſurpaſſing That of the <hi>Aerial Nocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luca,</hi> and this Light ſeems to proceed from, if not alſo to reſide in the Body it ſelf.</p>
                           <p n="7">7. When our <hi>Icy Phoſphorus</hi> is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of its receptacle, and expoſed to the immediate contact of the free Air, it uſually emits a wonderful
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48263:18"/> deal of Smoak, diſcernable by the Light of the Body it aſcends from; and this plentiful emiſſion of Efflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viums uſually laſts as long as the <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> is kept in the Air.</p>
                           <p n="8">8. But 'tis pleaſant to obſerve, and deſerves to be conſidered, That as ſoon as 'tis plung'd in Water, ſo as to be quite covered with that Liquor, it ceaſes not only to Smoak as before, but to ſhine, as if a thorowly kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled Coal were ſuddenly quenched in Water. And if it were not for this, our <hi>Noctiluca</hi> would effluviate ſo faſt, that it would be quickly waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; whereas the Water, fencing it from the contact of the Air, keeps it from ſpending it ſelf as formerly, and yet does really make but a ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and temporary extinction of this <hi>Anomalous</hi> Fire. For as ſoon as 'tis again taken out of the Water (though it have lain there perhaps a great while) it falls to ſhine again, even whilſt 'tis yet dropping wet.</p>
                           <p n="9">9. And I have ſometimes had the pleaſure to obſerve, that when I had
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48263:19"/> ſo large a Piece of <hi>Noctiluca,</hi> that I could conveniently hold one half of it under the Surface of the Water, and the other half above it, whilſt the emers'd part afforded no Light, the extant part ſhone Vividly.</p>
                           <p>Having thus mentioned moſt of the qualities that belong to the Nocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luca it ſelf, I ſhall now proceed to the <hi>Phaenomena,</hi> my Tryals on it, or with it afforded me, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining my ſelf to any ſolicitous order, ſince my Circumſtances permitted me not to keep one in making thoſe tryals. But before I deſcend to other Particulars, It will not, I think, be amiſs to take notice of a few, that, having more affinity than others with the laſt mentioned quality of our <hi>Phoſphorus,</hi> ſeem proper to be annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to what has been delivered of it.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:48263:19"/>
                     <head>OBSERVATIONS About The WATER Wherein the NOCTILUCA Was kept.</head>
                     <div n="4" type="section">
                        <head>
                           <hi>SECT.</hi> IV.</head>
                        <p>BEcauſe I gueſſed that the Water wherein the <hi>Noctiluca</hi> had been long kept covered, to fence it from the Air, though it did not manifeſtly diſſolve the Maſs, yet might be impregnated at leaſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48263:20"/> with the more <hi>Saline,</hi> and on that account reſoluble parts of it, I thought fit to make a few tryals upon this Liquor.</p>
                        <div n="1" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> I.</head>
                           <p>And Firſt, I found that it had a ſtrong and penetrant taſte, that ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed near of kin to that of Sea-Salt, but was more piercing, as if Brine were mingled with Spirit of Salt, and it reliſhed alſo ſomewhat of Vitriol.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> II.</head>
                           <p>Being put into a ſmall concave Veſſel of Refin'd Silver upon lighted Coals and Aſhes, it evaporated but very ſlowly, and would not be brought to ſhoot into Cryſtals, nor yet to afford a dry Salt, but coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into a Subſtance ſometimes like a Gelly, and ſometimes, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, like whites of Eggs; which Subſtance was eaſily melted by heat.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="experiment">
                           <pb n="25" facs="tcp:48263:20"/>
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experment</hi> III.</head>
                           <p>When this Subſtance was kept a while on a hotter Fire, it only boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at firſt, but ſoon after began, as I gueſſed it would, to make a crack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling noiſe; wherein, this was remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and pretty, that the Exploſions were accompanied with flaſhes of Fire and light, which if they were ſmall, were generally very Blew, like the Flames of Sulphur, but more Vivid, and ſometimes alſo more Blew; but the greater cracks, whoſe noiſe was conſiderable, were wont to appear of a Yellow colour and very Luminous. And theſe <hi>Phaenomena</hi> did not only appear whilſt the Matter was Boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over the Fire, but a pretty while after the Veſſel was taken off and held in the Air.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="4" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> IV.</head>
                           <p>If before the Coagulated Matter were too far waſted by the heat, it
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48263:21"/> were ſuffered to coole a little, it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have acquired a conſiſtence like melted Roſin, or rather ſtill Bird-Lime, for it would draw out into Threeds of, perhaps, a Foot or more in length; and having held one of theſe Threeds to the Flame of a Candle, it did not take Fire, but melted into little Globul's, as ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillary Threeds of Glaſs are in like circumſtances wont to do. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made ſome of them ſtick to the wieck of a Candle, towards the bottom of the Flame, they Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured the lower part of the flame quite round with a very fine Blew, which laſted much longer than one would have Expected.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="5" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> V.</head>
                           <p>This glutinous Subſtance had, by the Action of the Fire, acquired an odd kind of ſtrong ſmell, almoſt like That of Garlick, and being left all night in the Air, attracted to it (to uſe the Vulgar Phraſe) the moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48263:21"/> of it, exceeding faſt, being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in a good part into a Liquor almoſt as ſtrong as Spirit of Salt.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="6" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> VI.</head>
                           <p>Putting this Subſtance again over the Fire, as before, it appeared to be more fixt than one would have look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, for though there were not ſo much as a Spoonful of it, yet it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Boyling for a great while, and afforded a Multitude of ſhining <hi>Exploſions,</hi> whereof ſome made a conſiderable noiſe, and gave notable flaſhes of Light, which ſeemed to be made by condens'd and agitated Fumes, ſuppreſſed by the ſomewhat hardned Surface of the Matter, and kindled in their eruption into the Air, into which ſome parts of theſe Fumes, that were not kindled, eſcaped in the form of a Smoke, whoſe ſmell was very ſtrong and rank, but of a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar kind. To which I ſhall add, what ſeemed ſtrange, that though often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times two, and ſometimes more ſlaſhes
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48263:22"/> appeard at once, yet ſo ſmall a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Matter continued to afford them for almoſt an hour together, and probably would have done it longer, but that the late time of the Night obliged me to go to Bed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Experiment was finiſhed.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:48263:22"/>
                     <head>What Liquors would, or would not diſſolve, the <hi>Icy Noctiluca.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div n="5" type="section">
                        <head>
                           <hi>SECT.</hi> V.</head>
                        <p>AMong other ways of inveſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Nature of our <hi>Icy Phoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus,</hi> I thought fit to try, whether or no it would be diſſolved in ſome Liquors of differing kinds, hoping, that if it would be ſo in any of them, it might ſomewhat aſſiſt us to gueſs at its Texture.</p>
                        <div n="1" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> I.</head>
                           <p>We found then by tryal, That common Water would not in the Cold diſſolve it, though the Liquor was thereby Impregnated, as when <hi>Crocus Metallorum,</hi> or Glaſs of <hi>Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> being infuſed in Wine or Water,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48263:23"/> the Menſtruum will be Impregnated by its Emetick Particles, and yet the Bulk, Shape, and Colour of the Cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>us, or the Glaſs, will not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be viſibly diminiſhed or altered.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> II.</head>
                           <p>Afterwards we put a Grain or two of our Lucid Matter into a little Urinous Spirit of <hi>Sal Armoniac,</hi> but it ſeemed not to make any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict with it, nor manifeſtly to work upon it, though, to give the Liquor time to make a Solution, we left them together for ſeveral days. But as ſoon as we had poured aſide the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, it appeared that it had not by any contrariety deſtroy'd the power of the <hi>Noctiluca,</hi> which began readily to ſhine as formerly, and yet, might be immediately ſuppreſſed again, by ſuffering the Liquor to cover it as before; but when we had, by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Phial for ſome time in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate heat, Impregnated the Liquor with it, this Liquor, being then dropt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48263:23"/> into Water, had a like effect with That mentioned in the Experiment of Impregnated Spirit of Wine.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> III.</head>
                           <p>Seeing a Volatile and Urinous Salt would not work ſenſibly upon our <hi>Phoſphorus,</hi> we thought fit to try, what Corroſive Liquors would do, and accordingly, we put a Grain or two of our Splendent Matter into a very ſmall Phial, wherein was a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Oyl of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> that Menſtruum appearing, in many caſes, more Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſive, than other vulgar <hi>Acids,</hi> but neither did this Menſtruum diſſolve our <hi>Icy Noctiluca</hi> in the Cold, and therefore putting it in ſome heat, we found, that though it did not mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly diſſolve the ſhining Matter, yet the warmed Oyl made it melt, and appear at leaſt for the time a fluid Body; in which this ſeemed to me remarkable, that this ſo fugitive a Subſtance ſhould be ponderous enough to lye at the bottom of Oyl
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48263:24"/> of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> which is one of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieſt Fluids we yet know, except Quickſilver, which many will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low to be a Liquor. What we did with this melted <hi>Noctiluca</hi> was not unpleaſant to ſee, and will, God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting, be hereafter mentioned.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="4" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> IV.</head>
                           <p>Afterwards we put a ſmall Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our <hi>Icy Phoſphorus</hi> into <hi>Aqua-Fortis,</hi> and though we kept it in that Menſtruum, two or three Days, and ſet the Vial that contained them for many hours in a warm place, (the Chimney Corner) yet we found the Matter ſo little altered, as to its viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble appearance, that we doubted whether the Liquor had diſſolved any ſenſible quantity of it.</p>
                           <p>Having tryed Saline Menſtruums upon our <hi>Icy Phoſphorus,</hi> I thought fit to try Oyls, and alſo Spirit of Wine, that is reckoned by Chymiſts to be of great affinity with them.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="5" type="experiment">
                           <pb n="33" facs="tcp:48263:24"/>
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> V.</head>
                           <p>Whereupon I put a little of our <hi>Noctiluca</hi> into ſome Oyle of <hi>Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> which not diſſolving it in the Cold, the ſmall Vial that contained it, was left all Night in the Chimny upon warm Aſhes. But though the next Day none of the <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> appeared any longer in the Glaſs, yet we could not perceive by two or three differing Tryals, that the Oyle was much altered by it, and particularly I obſerved that though the Glaſs were unſtopt, and kept ſo for a while, yet the Ingreſs of the Air did not produce any ſenſible light, nor did we perceive the upper part of the Glaſs to be full of white Fumes, as is uſual in divers other Liquors Impregnated with our <hi>Noctiluca,</hi> when they are unſtopt.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="section">
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:48263:25"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>SECT.</hi> VI.</head>
                        <p>IT has rendred the Experiments made with the <hi>Aerial Noctiluca,</hi> much leſs acceptable, than otherwiſe they would have been, to the delicate ſort of Speculators, eſpecially to La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, that the Light they produced was accompanied with a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant ſmell, that iſſued out of the Phial whenever it was unſtopped, to let in the Air. But by the help of our <hi>Icy Noctiluca,</hi> I found a way to prevent this ungrateful concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant of our Artificial Light. But not being diſcouraged by the bad ſucceſs of the forementioned Experiment, I hoped an <hi>Aromatical</hi> Oyl might do, what <hi>Subtil</hi> Oyles had not done.</p>
                        <div n="1" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> I.</head>
                           <p>And therefore having in a very ſmall Phial put about a Grain of <hi>Nocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucal</hi> Matter, and cover'd it with as much pure Eſſential of <hi>Cinamon,</hi> as
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48263:25"/> would ſwim leſs than a Fingers breadth above it, we carefully ſtopt our little Phial, and having warily held the bottom of it againſt a Fire, till the <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> began to melt, I ſuffered it to Cool; and then unſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping it in a dark place, had the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſee produced a Vaniſhing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but a Vivid Light. So that by this means I could afterwards ſhew the production of Light to the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Perſons of Quality, not only without offending their Noſes, whilſt their Eyes were gratified, but with adding to the pleaſure of a delightful Apparition, That of a Fragrant ſmell. But becauſe Oyle of <hi>Cloves</hi> is more eaſie to be had good, than the Oyl of <hi>Cinamon,</hi> and is alſo much cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, I tryed the Experiment more fully with That, and therefore ſhall proceed to give you (for an Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Aromatick</hi> Oyles) the <hi>Phaeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena</hi> of it.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="experiment">
                           <pb n="36" facs="tcp:48263:26"/>
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> II.</head>
                           <p>We put ſome of our Luminous <hi>Ice</hi> into a little pure Oyl of <hi>Cloves,</hi> ſuch as the <hi>Chymiſts</hi> call Eſſential, but found after a conſiderable time (no leſs than ſome Days) that at leaſt a good part of the Matter was undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, but yet the Liquor was rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Impregnated by it, as we found by a pretty <hi>Phaenomenon</hi> that it afforded us. For the little Phial, it was kept in, being opened in a dark place, there immediately enſued a kind of flaſh of Light, far more Vivid, its ſmall Bulk conſidered, than any Liquor had afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us before. But the brightneſs of this Apparition was it ſeems too great to be laſting, for this Flame-like Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance uſually expired in leſs than a Minute of an Hour, ſometimes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in half that time. And there were two other Circumſtances par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular enough in this <hi>Phaenomenon; On<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>,</hi> that ſometimes, eſpecially if a Candle were in the Room, the ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48263:26"/> 
                              <hi>Fluid</hi> would appear of a pleaſant and ſomewhat ſurprizing Blewiſh Colour. And the <hi>Other,</hi> that the Light would ceaſe whilſt yet there remained in the upper part of the Glaſs pretty Store of Whitiſh Fumes, ſuch as we have formerly often Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the <hi>Aerial Noctiluca</hi> to be the uſual Cauſes or Concomitants of Light, as if in our preſent caſe the ſhining Subſtance prey'd on, or reſided in only the finer and more delicate Particles of the Whitiſh Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halations.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> III.</head>
                           <p>Inſtead of the Oyl of <hi>Cloves,</hi> we ſubſtitued ſome <hi>Chymical</hi> Oyl of <hi>Mace,</hi> into which we put a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent quantity of the Glacial <hi>Phoſpho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus;</hi> but though we warmed the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the Phial, at leaſt as much as we judged neceſſary, yet, upon the unſtopping of it, there appeared no ſign of Light, though the tryal was made much more than once or twice,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:48263:27"/> and ſometimes with favourable Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, which event was the leſs expected, becauſe the Oyl, made uſe of, was preſented me as very pure, by the ſame Traveller who gave me That of <hi>Cloves</hi> newly mentioned. And becauſe alſo the Warmed <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> was ſo well conditioned, that as ſoon as ever the Oyl was removed, it ſhone with a ſomewhat extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Vividneſs.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="4" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> IV.</head>
                           <p>We made alſo a Tryal or two with Diſtill'd and Fragrant Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds,</hi> to ſee, if That being an Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Oyl as <hi>Chymiſts</hi> ſpeak, and being look'd upon by many as a kind of <hi>Aromatick</hi> Oyl, it would better diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the <hi>Noctiluca,</hi> or be Impregnated by its <hi>Luciferous</hi> parts; but we found that it neither diſſolved the Matter, nor upon the unſtopping of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, that contain'd it, did it afford any Light, or ſo much as Whitiſh Fumes, which ſeemed ſomewhat ſtrange, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48263:27"/> the Oyl was very ſubtile, and by its aptneſs to <hi>Coagulate</hi> of it ſelf, ſhewed that it was Genuine, and not as Chymical Oyles that are Venal too frequently (if not moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) are, <hi>Sophiſticated.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>If theſe two laſt recited Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments prove conſtant, they will ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue that not every <hi>Fragrant,</hi> no, nor every <hi>Aromatical</hi> Oyl, properly ſo called, has the like operation upon our Noctilucal Matter, as the Oyl of <hi>Cloves</hi> and <hi>Cinamon</hi> have.</p>
                           <p>If I had had or could have procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red other Eſſential Oyls, on whoſe Genuineneſs I could have depended, I had try'd their effects upon our <hi>Phoſphorus.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="5" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> V.</head>
                           <p>But having no more Oyls fit for my turn, I next tryed whether I could diſſolve our ſhining Matter in Ardent Spirits, which are thought by <hi>Chymiſts</hi> to be of near Conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity with diſtill'd Oyls; (not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48263:28"/> now to enquire, whether they do not conſiſt of the finer parts of the highly rarified Oyl of Bodies, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a great proportion of their <hi>Phlegm</hi>) and having accordingly put ſome of our <hi>Icy Phoſphorus</hi> into the Spirit of wine, though the Menſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um did ſome hundreds of times ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the Body 'twas to work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet after divers days, wherein it ſtood in a Window, expoſed to the Sun Beams, in the hotteſt part of the Summer, it appeared undiſſolv'd at the bottom of the Liquor, and ſcarce ſenſibly diminiſhed. But of the ſeparation of Spirit of Wine upon the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter, further tryals will require, that more be ſaid hereafter.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:48263:28"/>
                     <head>Of a way of ſuddenly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Light in common Water, by the help of another, not Luminous, Liquor.</head>
                     <div n="7" type="section">
                        <head>
                           <hi>SECT.</hi> VII.</head>
                        <p>I Come now to recite to you a <hi>Phaenomenon</hi> which I preſume may not diſpleaſe you. I had a hint of it from a caſual Obſervation made by my induſtrious Laborant. For having, to incourage him, allow'd him for his own uſe ſome Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our <hi>Icy Noctiluca,</hi> he min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled a portion of this ſhining Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with a Spirituous Medicinal Liquor that he had prepared, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting ſeveral Drugs with it, and having afterwards upon ſome occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or other diluted it with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:48263:29"/> it afforded him a <hi>Phaenemenon,</hi> at which being ſurpriz'd, he came to acquaint me with it, bringing me withal ſome of the Liquor. But I thinking that the <hi>Phaenomenon</hi> did not depend upon the Peculiar Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Liquor, whoſe being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Compounded and high Coloured made me judge it not fit for <hi>Lucife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> Experiments, but proceeded from the Vinous Spirits wherein that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor abounded, I thought fit to make the Experiment with a Liquor as Colourleſs and Simple as I could. The effects of ſuch Liquors being more eaſie to be diſcerned, and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, and reaſoned upon. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly we weigh'd out in a tender Ballance one Grain of our <hi>Glacial Phoſphorus,</hi> wiped dry, and broken in four or five pieces, for the eaſier diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. And to theſe in a <hi>Cryſtalline</hi> Phial, we put a convenient quantity of highly Rectified Vinous Spirit, and ſtopping the Phial cloſe, we ſuffered the things contained in it, to remain for many hours, ſometimes (and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:48263:29"/> for the moſt part) in the Cold, and ſometimes in the Warm Sun, but perceived not that near a total diſſolution was made of the <hi>Noctilu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Matter by the Liquor in which it lay, even one of the leſſer Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments appearing, as well as the others, undiſſolved in the bottom of it. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſince a Body conſiſting of ſuch ſubtile parts may communicate many of them to a contiguous Liquor without any diminution of its Bulk, obſervable by the Eye, I thought fit to try what Effects this Body had upon the Vinous Spirit.</p>
                        <div n="1" type="observation">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Obſervation</hi> I.</head>
                           <p>And Firſt, I Obſerved, that it did not manifeſtly diſcolour the Liquor, but left it Tranſparent and Limpid, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſave that there appeared ſome very ſmall Earthy Corpuſcles, like Duſt at the bottom of the Liquor, when being a little ſhaken (to raiſe them) it was attentively view'd.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="observation">
                           <pb n="44" facs="tcp:48263:30"/>
                           <head>
                              <hi>Obſervation</hi> II.</head>
                           <p>We did not Obſerve that, upon the unſtopping of the Phial, and the reſtored commerce between the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and outward Air, there appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red any flame or Luminous Exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as is uſual upon opening Phials that contain the Liquid <hi>Aerial Nocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luca.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="observation">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Obſervation</hi> III.</head>
                           <p>But the <hi>Phaenomenon</hi> I chiefly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to relate was This, That, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in a dark Night dropt a little of this Impregnated Spirit into a ſmall <hi>China</hi> Cup, with common Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in it, though the Spirit neither in the Phial, nor in its paſſage through the Air, diſcloſed any degree of Luminouſneſs, yet as ſoon as ever the drops came to touch the Liquor, they would be as it were kindled by the Cold Water, and afford little flaſhes of Light, which was more
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:48263:30"/> Vivid than the <hi>Noctiluca</hi> it ſelf, afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Splendor that made not only the brims of the Cup, but divers of the Neighbouring Objects mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly Viſible, not to ſay conſpicuous. But theſe <hi>Coruſcations</hi> had the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of other Lightning, to vaniſh almoſt as ſoon as they appeared, nor would the Water, that produced them, by being agitated, ſhine; but others might immediately be produced, by letting freſh drops fall into the ſame Water, upon whoſe Surface they ſeemed to diffuſe themſelves, and would ſometimes leave for a little while a faintly Luminous as it were Film or Membrane.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="4" type="observation">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Obſervation</hi> IV.</head>
                           <p>And that it might not be thought that this accenſion (if I may ſo call it) was produced or occaſioned by any <hi>Antiperiſtaſis,</hi> which the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Men, and the generality even of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers,</hi> are pleaſed to fancy (whoſe Opinion I have in a particular di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:48263:31"/> examined) I thought fit to try, whether our <hi>Phenomenon</hi> would not be produced with <hi>hot</hi> Water as well as with <hi>cold,</hi> and accordingly I found that the Impregnated Spirit of Wine produced rather a greater than a leſſer Light in hot Water than it had done in cold.</p>
                           <p>One of my deſigns, I had in mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Experiment, being to examine a conjecture I had made about the great diffuſedneſs of the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter, the ſubtilty of whoſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles made me think they were not to be judged abſent where ever they were not numerous or agitated e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to be of themſelves Viſible: this I ſay being in my thoughts, I judg'd it not fit to put our Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Icy</hi> Matter into the Spirit of Wine at adventures. Wherefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in a very good Ballance weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out one Grain of our <hi>Noctiluca,</hi> (firſt wiped dry,) we put to it at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times, that it might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſſolve, above two thouſand Grains of Spirit of Wine, that would
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:48263:31"/> burn all away; and yet, which may ſeem ſtrange, this ſmall quantity of <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter did ſo Impregnate all the Liquor put upon it, that though nothing of Luminous did appear in the Menſtruum nor in any Exhalations riſing from it, though the Phial were unſtopped, or the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor poured out of it into the Air, yet as ſoon as ever 'twas dropt into common Water there would be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced a Vivid Apparition of Light, ſuch as has been a little above de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</p>
                           <p>It ſeemed not very improbable, that theſe ſuddain and vaniſhing flaſhes might, at leaſt in great part, proceed from the quick diſingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and extruſion of the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Particles, made by the Water, which, diluting the Vinous Spirit, diſabled them from retaining with them the Luciferous Corpuſcles. As if into one Ounce of high rectified Spirit of Wine, you put half a Dram, or a Dram of <hi>Camphire,</hi> the Liquor will diſſolve it, without being thereby manifeſtly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:48263:32"/> altered as to Colour or Tranſparen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; but if you drop this ſolution into common Water, the Vinous Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits will immediately diffuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the Liquor, and let go the Corpuſcles of the <hi>Camphire,</hi> which will Float like a White Powder up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Surface of the Water. To this Conjecture is agreeable what up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Tryal we Obſerved with our Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnated Spirit of Wine namely, that being dropt into other, well <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flegmed</hi> Spirit of Wine, we ſaw no Light produced; but when it was dropt into an Urinous Spirit of <hi>Sal Armoniac,</hi> which ſeems to conſiſt of the Volatile Salt diſſolved in the Phlegm or Aqueous Liquor, the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Corpuſcles by this Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh part were freed from the Vinous Spirits, almoſt as much as they would have been by common Water, and did accordingly ſhine with much briskneſs.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:48263:32"/>
                     <head>EXPERIMENTS Diſcovering a Strange SUBTILTY Of parts in the GLACIAL NOCTILUCA.</head>
                     <div n="8" type="section">
                        <head>
                           <hi>SECT.</hi> VIII.</head>
                        <p>BUT what has been above re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, is not all that I thought fit to try with the ſhining Matter, that I told you we diſſolved in Spirt of Wine, for after having, as I lately recited, brought one Grain to Impregnate between four and five Ounces of <hi>Alcohol,</hi> as the <hi>Chymiſts</hi> call the high Rectified
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:48263:33"/> Spirit of Wine, which did at leaſt two thouſand times exceed the weight of the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter, I preſum'd that this very parcel of Spirit of Wine, wherein the ſhining Matter was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready diffuſed and ſcattered into ſo many thouſand <hi>Corpuſcles,</hi> as ſufficed to Impregnate all the Liquor, would yet communicate to a good quantity of Water Particles enough to make it ſhine, when agitated, wherefore when we had weighed out in a very truſty Ballance one Dram of our Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnated Spirit of Wine, we mixed it with, and ſhook it in as much fair Water as we thought fit, (but not all at once) that is till we had to our Dram of Spirit of Wine, put above fifty times its weight of Water, and that <hi>Alcohol</hi> it ſelf weighing at leaſt two thouſand times as much as the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter, that Impregnated it, it follows, (though it may ſeem ſtrange it ſhould be true,) that the ſingle Grain of <hi>Icy Noctiluca</hi> was able to Diffuſe it ſelf through, and Impregnate full a hundred thouſand Grains of Liquor,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:48263:33"/> ſo as (when duly ordered) to make it Luminous. For having preſently after the laſt Water was put into the Glaſs, ſtopt the Veſſel Cloſe with a good Cork, and ſhaken it a little in a dark place, the whole Phial appeared to be full of Light, which though it were not more than ordinary intenſe, yet by reaſon of the Bulk of the Liquor made a glorious ſhew, and diſcovered di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the Neighbouring Objects. And after we had done ſhaking that Phial, not only the upper part, which was fill'd with Exhalations and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, ſhined like thoſe other Liquid <hi>Phoſphoruſſes</hi> formerly mentioned, but what was not obſerved in Them, the Water it ſelf had a Luminouſneſs, though of an inferiour degree, of its whole Maſs, which yet will not keep me from thinking of ſome expedient that may ſatisfie thoſe who may ſuſpect, as I did, that ſome of this Light proceeded from the Exhalations that ſhined through that <hi>Diaphanous</hi> Water, though this did not ſeem the only nor perhaps the chief cauſe of its appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:48263:34"/> Luminous, ſince when the Glaſs was ſhaken, the whole Maſs of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor appeared to ſhine, ſo that we could plainly ſee through the ſides of the Veſſel, the Conical Figure of its bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom.</p>
                        <p>After this, I proſecuted the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a good way further, encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the proportion of the Water to freſh Impregnated Spirit, and I found (what perhaps you will think ſtrange) that one part of the <hi>Noctiluca,</hi> being firſt diſſolved in <hi>Alcohol</hi> of Wine, and afterwards briskly ſhaken into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient quantity of Water, rendred Luminous as much Liquor, as upon Calculation amounted to four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand times its Weight. And this did not ſeem to proceed from the Irradiation of the Luminous Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſcles or Exhalations, ſhining in the empty ſpace at the top of the Glaſs; becauſe the Phial was ſo near fill'd with Liquor, that there was but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle room left for Vapours; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe alſo, the Vapours, that did play in that ſpace, ſhined but very
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:48263:34"/> faintly, and when the Glaſs was at reſt much leſs than a minute of an hour, the Light would reach but a little way downwards in the Water, and yet was there ſo dim, as to be ſcarce diſcernable. Whereas in our Experiment, not only the agitated Liquor appeared Luminous through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, but the Light was brisk enough, inſomuch that the <hi>Conical</hi> Figure of the bottom of the Glaſs was clearly viſible by the help of it.</p>
                        <p>But leſt ſome ſhould think, that if this Experiment had been further and further proſecuted, the Lumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs would have ſtill extended to greater and greater quantities of Water, I ſhall add, that when I encreaſed the proportion of this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor to the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter, to be diſperſed through it, by putting in near three or four ounces of Water, more than I gueſſed would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, the Luminous Matter ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be as it were drowned or loſt in ſo much Liquor, for though we gave it much more agitation, than
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:48263:35"/> had in the former Experiments been needful to produce Light, yet no Luminouſneſs at all appeared in the mixture. Wherefore, taking ſome freſh Spirit, and ſhaking it into ſuch a quantity of Water, as I thought it might ſerve to Impregnate, I found by Supputation, that the Luminous Maſs of Liquor, thereby produced, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to no leſs, but a pretty deal more, than five hundred thouſand times the Weight of the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter diſperſed through it, which is a viſible expanſion, very much greater, than, I think, has been hitherto obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in any Corporeal Subſtance diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in a viſible Liquor, ſince it four times exceeds that expanſion of <hi>Cochineal,</hi> which I many years ſince imparted to the ingenious, and which ſeveral of them have in their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, been pleaſed to take notice of, as a prodigious thing; one part of the <hi>Cochineal,</hi> ordered as I there menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, having in that Experiment pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced a diſcernable Colour in an hundred twenty five thouſand parts
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:48263:35"/> of Water. To what has been ſaid, I ſhall add theſe three Circumſtances, which may encreaſe the ſtrangeneſs of the Experiment.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. The firſt is, that I here only delivered the manifeſt Impregnation of the Water it ſelf, which is a groſs and tangible Liquor, by the diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Particles of the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter, but have made no eſtimate of the incomparably greater expanſion of the Light, that from the Matter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the Phial, illuminated the Ambient Air, to a conſiderable diſtance from it, though by reaſon the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened Room was not great, I was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to make an Eſtimate how far the Enlightened Sphere of Air might have extended.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. The Second is, that this Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was not favourably made, but rather invidiouſly, ſince we purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weighed out ſomewhat leſs of the lucid Matter, and now and then more of the Water, than the preciſe quantities that calculation ſuppoſes,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:48263:36"/> that I might be ſure the Experiment was made ſeverely enough.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. And laſtly, upon ſearch I found that the grain of <hi>Icy Phoſphorus,</hi> that was firſt put into the Spirit of Wine, we made uſe of all this while, was not, though after ſo long a time, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally diſſolved; a ſmall Fragment, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting to about an eighth part, if not more, remaining at the bottom of the Phial; upon which having poured ſome freſh <hi>Alcohol</hi> of Wine, and kept it a while in a little heat, to further the diſſolution, I found That Liquor did, as I thought it would, grow very Luminous, when dropt into common Water, ſo that it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed probable, that if the whole Grain of <hi>Icy Phoſphorus</hi> had been diſſolved at firſt in the Spirit of Wine, it would have Impregnated above ſix hundred thouſand times its weight of Water, ſufficient to make it ſhine.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="section">
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:48263:36"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>SECT.</hi> IX.</head>
                        <p>I Come now to another way, by which I thought the great Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty of parts in our <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter might appear with good advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and poſſibly you will think by the ſucceſs, that I miſſed not of what I expected from the intended Tryal.</p>
                        <div n="1" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> I.</head>
                           <p>We carefully weighed out a ſmall lump of our ſhining Matter, amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to three Grains, and having pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely broken it into divers leſſer Fragments, perhaps ſix or ſeven at leaſt, we laid them upon a flat bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom'd Glaſs, that was broader at the top than the bottom, and ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low too, (not being near an Inch deep) that the Matter might be more fully expoſed to the free Air. This Glaſs we placed in a South Window, laying it very ſhelving, that the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:48263:37"/> to be produced, by its reſolution in the moiſt Air, might preſently run down, and not hinder the free Evaporation of the remaining Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. In which poſture of the Glaſs, we had alſo another aim, to be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after mentioned. The Veſſel being thus placed, about ten of the Clock at Night, all the Fragments of the <hi>Noctiluca</hi> ſhined briskly, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to do, till moſt of them were reſolved into other Subſtances, and the biggeſt of them continued to ſhine till they were reduced to ſuch a ſmallneſs, that they would ſcarce have been ſeen, had not their own Light made them viſible. But the main thing that I am to take notice of in this Experiment, (and which perhaps will ſomewhat ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize you,) is, that ſo little quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter continued to emit viſible Fumes for a good many more than an hundred and fifty Hours, and this with Circumſtances that made the thing more ſtrange.</p>
                           <p n="1">1. As Firſt, That this Smoke was not only viſible but manifeſt, and that
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48263:37"/> as well in the Night (as I often obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from time to time) as in the Day.</p>
                           <p n="2">2. Secondly, That the ſeveral Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of Matter did each emit there Fumes all at once, as if it were from ſo many little Chimneys.</p>
                           <p n="3">3. Thirdly, That this Smoke was ſo Copious, and withall ſo Tenaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that it would eaſily retain the form of Smoke at a conſiderable diſtance from the Bodies that emitted it, ſo that as I walked to and fro in the Room, a careleſs look towards the Glaſs would often diſcover it to me, and ſometimes it would mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly appear at a diſtance, that I eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated to be near a Foot from the Matter that afforded it.</p>
                           <p>I ſhall now add, to another purpoſe, the following Circumſtances; namely,</p>
                           <p n="1">1. Firſt, That the motion of the Smoke was ſwift enough, conſidering that it had no Channel or Chimny to aſſiſt it. It was not always, nor for the moſt part, directly upwards, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Horizontal, ſometimes down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, ſometimes towards the right
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:48263:38"/> hand, and ſometimes towards the left, as if the motion of the Fumes had been determined by the ſituation of thoſe parts of the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by which they were emitted, and as 'twere diſcharged; I uſe this laſt expreſſion, becauſe taking pleaſure to watch attentively the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of our delightful Experiment, I thought, I many times obſerved a kind of Palpitation or Aeſtuation in the little ſhining Fragments, which I gathered from the Apparent great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality I perceived in the plenty of the Smoke, that was emitted at ſeveral times, all of them perhaps within the compaſs of a minute or two. But on this I forbear to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, till I ſhall have made further obſervations; and therefore I ſhall proceed to take notice of one Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance more in our Experiment; which is,</p>
                           <p n="2">2. Secondly, That even in the latter part of it, after the ſhining Matter had been ſo long expoſed to the Air, it emitted a ſmell ſtrong enough;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:48263:38"/> which ſeemed to be cauſed by odorous Exhalations, diſtinct from the viſible Fumes.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="section">
                        <head>
                           <hi>SECT.</hi> X.</head>
                        <p>AND now 'tis time that I give you ſome account of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, (that I but pointed at before,) why I choſe ſuch a Glaſs, and kept it in a ſhelving poſture; this I did, that I might not loſe, but preſerve the Liquor, which I knew would fall from the Saline part of the ſhining Matter, which Liquor I thought fit to Examine in order to diſcover cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain things; particularly, whether the Limpid Water, as it appeared to be, that was as 'twere the <hi>Cadaver,</hi> or, to employ <hi>Chymical</hi> terms, the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quated <hi>Caput Mortuum,</hi> of the ſhining ſubſtance, did not yet contain ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as well Luminous as Saline.</p>
                        <div n="1" type="experiment">
                           <pb n="62" facs="tcp:48263:39"/>
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> I.</head>
                           <p>To ſatisfie my ſelf about this, I cauſed this Liquor to be put into a ſmall concave Veſſel of carefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined Silver (that other Salts than <hi>Nitre</hi> and <hi>Allum</hi> might not <hi>Corrode</hi> it) which I had purpoſely provided for the quick Evaporation and Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtallization of ſmaller quantities of Matter. Our Liquor, being in this Veſſel put upon ſome ſmall Coals and Aſhes, did not Evaporate near ſo eaſily, as one would have thought, but turned into an <hi>
                                 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nctuous</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, of a dark Reddiſh Colour; wherefore we placed the Veſſel up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on quick Coals, that by their brisk heat they might make the Liquor boil, and free it from ſuperfluous moiſture. By this means after a while it was reduced to a Subſtance that afforded us a pretty <hi>Phaenomenon,</hi> not unlike to That elſewhere men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, where we ſpake of the Infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or Solution of the Solid <hi>Phoſpho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi>
                              <pb n="63" facs="tcp:48263:39"/> in common Water. For the boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Liquor crackled like a handful of Bay-Salt caſt into the Fire, and whilſt theſe cracklings continued, (which they did much longer than one would have expected) they imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated little Volleys of Shot, not only in the great number of the Noiſes they made, but in the little ſlaſhes that accompanied them, which flaſhes, when the Fire was ſomewhat encreaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, were ſo many, and followed one another ſo faſt, that they appeared to make up a continued flame, not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant to behold.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> II.</head>
                           <p>After the foregoing Experiment, I had a mind to be able to make ſome eſtimate, how far the breaking of the ſhining Matter into Fragments, and the conditions of the Veſſel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the quick conſumption of it. To this purpoſe, we took a lump of three Grains, carefully weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, and put it into a ſmall Glaſs
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:48263:40"/> Funnel, whoſe upper end was wide and capacious enough, in reference to the lower part, which was exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſlender, that the <hi>Noctiluca</hi> might have Air both above and (often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times) below, and yet the Matter might not ſide down, till it were ſo waſted, as to be leſs than a ſmall Pins head; a Veſſel of this ſhape I choſe to make uſe of, that I might catch the Liquor, that would be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded by the deliquation of our <hi>Icy Phoſphorus;</hi> for which purpoſe the ſlender pipe of this Funnel was put into the Orifice of a ſmall <hi>Cylindri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Phial, and there kept in a quiet place, which was a South-Window, from whence every Night, after I was in Bed, I cauſed it to be brought into my Chamber, to ſee if it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to ſhine. By which Tryals, I found that it remained Luminous, and was not yet ſo waſted, to fall quite through the Funnel into the Phial, at ſomewhat beyond the end of the Fifteenth day; ſo that it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to ſhine, three hundred and ſixty Hours.</p>
                           <pb n="65" facs="tcp:48263:40"/>
                           <p>The very Limpid Liquor, that was brought into the Phial by this Experiment, was unhappily loſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I could make any Tryals with it, but not before I had done the chief thing I aimed at, in ſaving of it, which was to know its weight to be by and by mentioned.</p>
                           <p>What has been hitherto related, may juſtly enough make a Man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect, with ſome wonder, upon the ſtrange minuteneſs and multitude of parts, that are crouded together in our <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter; if we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what a multitude of Luminous Beams of viſible Smoke, of Odora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, though unſeen, Eſfluviums, ſo ſmall a quantity of it, as three Grains, which are but the twentieth part of a Drachm, could inceſſantly afford for two or three hundred hours; leaving after all this behind it above three times its Weight, (for ſo we found it to be) of a Liquor, which it ſelf was not a Cadavorous one, or, what it looked like, common Water,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:48263:41"/> but (as may be argued from what was lately recited of the ſame kind of Liquor) might have been Impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated with very many Saline parts, and not a few capable of ſhining briskly.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:48263:41"/>
                     <head>OBSERVATIONS About the INFLAMABILITY Of the NOCTILUCA It ſelf.</head>
                     <div n="11" type="section">
                        <head>
                           <hi>SECT.</hi> XI.</head>
                        <div n="1" type="observation">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Obſervation</hi> I.</head>
                           <p>I Took a little of the Conſiſtent <hi>Noctiluca,</hi> and having broken it, and, as its brittleneſs would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, ſpread it here and there, upon a piece of folded Paper, I lighted that
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:48263:42"/> Paper at the flame of a Candle, and obſerved, that when the flame reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed This or That little Fragment of the ſhining Matter, it would take Fire, and burn away in a ſlaſhing and very ſputtering manner, accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with noiſe, almoſt as Grains of Salt <hi>Petre</hi> are wont to do, when they are put upon a live Coal.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="observation">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Obſervation</hi> II.</head>
                           <p>I obſerved alſo, that if I put pieces of Paper, on which I had placed ſome of theſe Grains of <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter, upon ſome Embers covered with Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, before the paper it ſelf took Fire, the ſhining Matter would communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate its flame to the Contiguous Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="1" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> I.</head>
                           <p>We took a Fragment of our ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Matter, not amounting to a Grain, This we put into half a Spoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or leſs of high Rectified Spirit of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:48263:42"/> Wine, and kindling that Liquor with the flame of a Candle, the Spirit burned away, as is uſual, in a-flame partly Yellow, (and eſpecially at the out ſide) but chiefly Blew: But though the heat of the Silver Spoon, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Tryal was made, did quickly (as might well be expected) melt the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter, and gave it a Globular form, yet it continued at the bottom without manifeſtly mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Vinous Spirits, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably altering the Colour of their flame: But when the Spirit of Wine was all conſumed, without leaving any jot of Phlegm behind it, the laſt drops coming, when they were actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally kindled, to touch the ſhining Matter, preſently ſet it a Fire, but its flame was very differing from that of the Vinous Spirits. For beſides ſomewhat that was odd in its Figure, its Colour was not at all Blew, or Blew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, but of an intenſe Yellow, and burned ſo fiercely, and with ſo Vivid a Light, as was ſomewhat ſurpriſing to behold, and continued to Burn a
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:48263:43"/> pretty while, conſidering the paucity of the combuſtible Matter. And whilſt it burned, it emitted good ſtore of Smoke, that ſeemed to be darted up to a conſiderable height, the Matter did not burn all away at firſt, but left a kind of <hi>Caput Mortuum,</hi> which lay in the form of a little Cake, partly of a deep Yellow, and partly of a fine Red. This Matter being more Bulky in proportion to That, That was conſumed, than I thought it likely that ſo little of the <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> ſhould contain of incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtible Matter, I proceeded to burn it, as elſewhere will be related af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another manner, till there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained but ſome very few light fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that ſeemed to be of the ſame nature, with Thoſe that are to be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the next Experiment.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> II.</head>
                           <p>We took a ſmall Fragment, not amounting to a Grain of the <hi>Nocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucal</hi> Matter, and putting it into a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:48263:43"/> Silver Spoon, we caſt upon it the Sun-beams concentrated by our ſmall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>(Dioptrical)</hi> burning Glaſs; by Theſe it was preſently ſet on Fire, and afforded, together with a great deal of Smoke, a flame exceeding Yellow, and ſo very fierce and bright, that it was conſpicuous; though the Window being purpoſely ſet open, the Beams of the Sun, then in the <hi>Meridian,</hi> were ſuffered to beat full upon it, and a brisk Wind did alſo blow upon it without extinguiſhing it. At the bottom of the Spoon, the expiring flame left a round and broad <hi>Caput Mortuum,</hi> conſiſting of divers Circles, like thoſe of a <hi>Sardonix,</hi> whereof the largeſt was White, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Yellow, and the third Red, all the three Colours being Pleaſant and Vivid enough. Some part of this <hi>Caput Mortuum,</hi> being again brought to be freely touched by the Air, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared Combuſtible, and the reſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing left in the Spoon, that the Air might work upon it, did for the moſt part ſoon reſolve it ſelf <hi>per De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquium</hi>
                              <pb n="72" facs="tcp:48263:44"/> into a Liquor, almoſt as ſharp as Spirit of Salt, the reſt being a light Black Feculency, of which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there was ſo very little of it, we could make no Examen.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> III.</head>
                           <p>Being deſirous to try, whether the <hi>Nectilucal</hi> Matter would, by bare preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or motion, be brought to Burn, I thought not fit to depend upon ſuch other Experiments, as are here related, wherein it appears able to ſet Fire on divers Bodies, belonging to the vegetable kingdom, or are otherwiſe eaſily inflamable, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we put two Grains of our dryed <hi>Nectilucal</hi> Matter into a Glaſs Morter (furniſhed with a Glaſs Peſtle) whoſe coldneſs and thickneſs were able to keep it from being put into any ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible heat by the operation, that was to be performed in it, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently from communicating any heat of <hi>its own</hi> to the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. This was pretty briskly rubbed
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:48263:44"/> in the Morter, with the Glaſs Peſtle, but though it was thereby brought to ſhine much more Vividly than before, yet it did not take Fire, which I was apt to impute to the great cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Glaſs, which much oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Incaleſcence</hi> of the <hi>Phoſphorus,</hi> but after a while longer it took Fire, and began to burn away in an actual flame, with much Smoke: But this did not laſt ſo long, as might have been expected, which ſhort duration might proceed from the Veſſel, that continued ſenſibly cold, and perhaps alſo from the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowneſs, and depth of it, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what hindred the free acceſs of the Air; for ſome Matter, that was taken out on the Peſtle, ſeemed to Burn bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than That which remained in the Morter, which being extinguiſhed, was once more kindled by Triturati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but ſoon expiring again, could not by the ſame means be rekindled, but only was brought to ſhine brisk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:48263:45"/>
                     <head>EXPERIMENTS About BURNING Other BODIES With the NOCTILUCA.</head>
                     <div n="12" type="section">
                        <head>
                           <hi>SECT.</hi> XII.</head>
                        <p>I Formerly intimated that our conſiſtent <hi>Noctiluca,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the appearance it had of <hi>Ice,</hi> and its actual Coldneſs to the touch, was much diſpoſed to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:48263:45"/> have its parts eaſily put into motion, and might by that means be brought to be ſenſibly hot. And I think it time now to proceed to make this good by particular Inſtances.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. And Firſt, If our <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> be for any time preſſed hard between ones Fingers, or againſt a Board, or ſome ſuch hard and not very cold Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, it will oftentimes be felt actually and very ſenſibly hot, and ſometimes the degree of heat will be ſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as to Scorch the Skin, as my venturous Laborant found ſeveral times to his no ſmall pain, his Fingers being almoſt covered with Bliſters raiſed on them, by handling our ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Matter, with too bold a curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity: And he complained to me, that, though according to the uſual fate of <hi>Chymiſts,</hi> he had been often Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on other occaſions, yet he ſound Bliſters, excited by the <hi>Phoſphorus,</hi> more painful than others; and he is not the only perſon that has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to me of their finding the Burning made with this Matter to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:48263:46"/> be more tedious and difficult to be cured, than ordinary ones. But, as our <hi>Noctiluca</hi> was not always made of the ſame Matter, nor with care e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually ſucceſsful, ſo I obſerved its proneneſs to incaleſcence, and the degrees of heat, to which it would be brought by motion, to be differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enough; upon which account, I did not find, that ſome portions of it, would produce thoſe higher effects of heat, that ſome others did, beſides that theſe higher effects did gradually differ among themſelves.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Agreeably to this, after having in vain tryed to Fire Paper by preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and rubbing ſome of our <hi>Phoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus</hi> upon it with the blade of a Knife, I took a piece of fine Paper, and having dry'd, and warm'd it at the Fire, I put a little of our <hi>Noctilu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> in a fold of it, and rubbing the Paper between my hands, though by tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> attrition there were produced a ſenſible, and even conſiderable heat, yet it did not reach to what I deſired, but con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>uing a little while to rub
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:48263:46"/> the Paper to and fro, it did on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain take Fire, and blazed out, ſo that it would have Burned my hand, if This had not been kept from recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>much</hi> harm (for <hi>all</hi> it did not eſcape) by a thin Glove, that was thereby ſcorched, and in part ſhrivel'd up. After the ſame manner, to make the Experiment the more certain, I fired another piece of Paper, but then deſiſted, that I might not unneceſſarily waſte a Subſtance, wherewith I was but meanly ſtored.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. If the firing of Gun-powder could be performed with our <hi>Phoſpho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> without the aſſiſtance of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, whoſe difficult concourſe will keep it from being more than an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Curioſity; the fear that it might be applied to uſes miſchievous to Men, would keep me ſilent of the power our <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> may be brought to have of kindling Gun-powder, when 'tis befriended with favourable Circumſtances. To try therefore, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our <hi>Phoſphorus,</hi> which appeared not inferiour to That of Mr. <hi>Craft</hi>'s, would (as His did ſometimes, though not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly)
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:48263:47"/> fire Gun-powder, we took a little of our ſhining Matter, and having a little wiped it, to dry it, we put it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome dry Gun-powder, and with a Knife preſſed it, and in ſome ſort rubbed it upon the Black Grains, but found, that though a heat were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, and ſometimes ſuch as would make ſome of the <hi>Corns</hi> of Powder have a Blewiſh flame, yet the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would not go off: So that the Laborant, to whom I left the care of reiterating the Experiment in my preſence, preſuming it would not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, ſcrupled not to hold his Head over it, that he might the better ſee what change was made in the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but then upon a ſudden the powder took Fire, and the flame ſhoot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, caught hold of his Hair, which made a Blaze, that proving in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent enough, became more diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, than the ſmell of the Smoke that ſucceeded it was delightful.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. But the ſame Laborant, who was very helpful to me in varying the preparation of the <hi>Phoſphorus,</hi> had a
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:48263:47"/> worſe miſadventure not long after, for bringing me ſome newly Diſtill'd Grains of our <hi>Noctiluca,</hi> covered with ſome of the ſhining Water, that came over with it, he unluckily broke the Glaſs in his Pocket, whereupon the heat of his Body, encreaſed by the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his long walk had put it into, did ſo excite the Matter, that was fallen out of the broken Phial, that it Burned two or three great holes in his Breech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, before he could come to me to relate his misfortune, the recent effects of which I could not look upon without ſome wonder as well as ſmiles.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. Having already told you the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of our <hi>Noctiluca</hi> upon Gun-powder; I thought fit to try, whether it would not kindle a Bodie, that is thought ſomewhat leſs prone to take fire.<note place="margin">Exper.</note> And accordingly having put together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout half a Grain of our dry <hi>Nocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucal</hi> Matter, and ſix times its weight of common flowers of Sulphur, they were lodged in the fold of a Piece of White Paper which was laid upon a Board, and when I had a little bruis'd
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:48263:48"/> and rubb'd This with the Haft of a Knife, it ſhone through the intercep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Paper very Vividly, but did no more: Wherefore, ſuſpecting that the want of Air was the cauſe why it did but ſhine, not burn too, I opened the Paper, and found that as ſoon as the Air had acceſs, it took Fire and furiouſly Burned the Paper, and, if I had not been wary, had burned me too. Another time, the ſame Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being try'd, afforded this nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Phaenomenon,</hi> that the Ingredients, being well rubb'd together in folded Paper, though before the Paper was diſplaid and expoſed to the Air, they did not kindle, yet upon the contact of This, the mixture took Fire, and did not burn away with a ſlow flame, as Brimſtone is wont to do, but ſlaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away at once with a great blaze, like Fired Gun-powder, ſave that the flame appeared more Luminous.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. The higheſt effect of the heat of our <hi>Icy Noctiluca</hi> was caſually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the Laborant, who being deſirous to try, whether ſome that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:48263:48"/> was newly prepared was good and fit to be brought to me, began to Write Letters with it, upon a piece of Planck, that had been long uſed in the Laboratory as part of a Stove, and he, chancing to preſs the recent Matter hard upon this Board, that the conſtant heat of the place had brought to an unuſual degree of dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, found to his ſurprize, that he had not only ſhining but burning Letters: The Lucid Matter having actually ſet on Fire thoſe parts of the Wood, againſt which he had ſtrongly preſſed it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="section">
                        <pb n="82" facs="tcp:48263:49"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>SECT.</hi> XIII.</head>
                        <div n="1" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> I.</head>
                           <p>TO examine ſomewhat particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, to what Family, or Sort of Salts, the <hi>Saline</hi> part of our <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter either does belong, or has moſt cognation with (for I thought it poſſible it might not fully agree with any known <hi>Species</hi> of Salts, but have ſomewhat peculiar to it ſelf) I ſuffered a little of the ſmall ſtock, I then had, to reſolve it ſelf <hi>per Deliquium</hi> into a clear Liquor, and then made with it ſome of the Tryals elſewhere delivered, by which I am wont to examine what <hi>Species</hi> a Salt belongs to, gueſſing this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor by the taſte, and the manner how it was made, to be ſomewhat, though not altogether, of the nature of Spirit of Sea-Salt: I dropt a little o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap> upon a convenient proportion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>rup of Violets, and found that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> it not Green, as a Volatile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> Salt would have done, but
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:48263:49"/> of a fine Carnation Colour, ſuch as that Syrup is wont to acquire, upon the mixture of an <hi>Acid</hi> Spirit with it. I found alſo, that a very little of our <hi>Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malous</hi> Liquor preſently deſtroy'd the blew Colour, and not the other of a Tincture of <hi>Lignum Nephriticum.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> II.</head>
                           <p>I alſo put ſome of this Liquor, that came by <hi>Deliquium</hi> from the <hi>Noctiluca,</hi> upon ſome ſilings of Copper, which being thorowly wetted, and ſome of them covered with it, I expoſed in a hollow Glaſs for two or three Days to the Air: and by this means had, as I expected, without the help of heat, a ſolution of ſome of the Filings of Copper, the Colour of which was not a deep <hi>Azure,</hi> as if it had been made with a Volatile Urinous Salt; but ſeemed to partake of Green and Blew, and to be an intermediate or Compounded Colour.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> III.</head>
                           <p>To make the Saline nature of this Liquor the more manifeſt, I put ſome
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:48263:50"/> of it upon powder of Red <hi>Coral,</hi> which it preſently fell upon, and Corroded with noiſe and froth; and putting another parcel of the ſame Liquor, upon ſome dry Salt of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> there preſently enſued a fierce conflict between them, whereby ſome noiſe and much froth was produced; ſo that I thought it needleſs to waſte any more of the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter, (wherewith I was but ſlenderly ſtored) to make it more apparent, that our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor was not, as moſt <hi>Chymiſts</hi> would have expected, of an Urinous nature, but belong'd to the Family of <hi>Acid</hi> Salts, and ſeemed to be near of kin to that branch of them, to which the Spirituous part of common or Sea-Salt belongs.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="4" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> IV.</head>
                           <p>Some Virtuoſi may be apt to think, that ſince our <hi>Icy Noctiluca</hi> is of a more Solid Subſtance than the <hi>Aerial,</hi> and uſes to continue to ſhine much longer, ſince I ſay this is ſo, if the conſiſtent
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:48263:50"/> 
                              <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> were included in a Glaſs, whence its expirations could have no vent, the Matter being kept from waſting, the Luminouſneſs may alſo be kept from ceaſing. This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture being plauſible, though the Notion I have of the Nature of our <hi>Noctiluca,</hi> could not promiſe me a confirmation of the conjecture, yet, to prevent the being blamed for an eaſily evitable omiſſion, I put ſome of our dry <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> into a clear Phial, capable, as was gueſſed, to hold about an Ounce of Water, and having very carefully cloſed this Glaſs, I laid it aſide, and obſerved it to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to ſhine for ſome few days, after which the Light manifeſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed, and ſoon after quite diſappea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, though I thought it poſſible, that it did not altogether ſo ſoon expire, as it ceaſed to be viſible to me; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Whitiſh Fumes, emitted by the Matter, whilſt it continued to ſhine, had covered the inſide of the Glaſs, with a kind of Whitiſh Soot, that at length opacating it, might well
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:48263:51"/> hinder a faint Light from pervading the Veſſel and reaching our Eyes. But it ſeems, that the Air included with the <hi>Phoſphorus,</hi> either had ſome vital Subſtance (if I may ſo call it) prey'd upon thereby, or elſe was by the Fumes of the <hi>Phoſphorus,</hi> to name no other poſſible ways, tamed and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at length unfit to continue the ſlame <hi>[ſui generis]</hi> of our <hi>Noctiluca.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="5" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> V.</head>
                           <p>Yet to purſue the deſign of making a Light more laſting than ordinary, by keeping the Matter from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with the External Air, I took ſome of our <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter, that came over with the Aqueous, from which 'twas not ſo eaſily ſeparable, but that I thought it beſt to leave them together, in regard that it ſhone ſo well, that it might paſs for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent portion of the <hi>Aerial Noctilu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca:</hi> This we Sealed up in a Glaſs-Egg (whoſe bottom had been made flat on purpoſe, that it might ſtand
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:48263:51"/> without leaning) and ſetting it in a place, where it would be frequently in my Eyes, I obſerved it from time to time, eſpecially at Night, and found it continue to ſhine (if I much miſremember not) a Week or longer, and that with ſo little decay of Light, that I was ſurpriz'd, when, coming in the Night time to look upon it, I found it to ſhine no more at all, eſpecially ſince I could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore any manifeſt light to it, either by agitation, or by moderately warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sealed Glaſs, that contained it.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="6" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> VI.</head>
                           <p>After many Obſervations made of the degrees of Light, that our <hi>Icy Noctiluca</hi> afforded, as 'twere of its own accord, without external heat, I thought fit to try whether by the application of a moderate heat of the Fire, the Light might not be much invigorated, and perhaps the <hi>Phoſpho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> it ſelf be brought actually to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:48263:52"/> even in a Cloſe Veſſel. This Deſign, I was the rather induced to proſecute, becauſe I had ſome hopes, that by this way of encreaſing the Light of our <hi>Phoſphorus,</hi> though it ſhould not long retain its acquired degree of Luminouſneſs, yet this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe might continue long enough for ſome not inconſiderable uſes. And eſpecially (in caſe much <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter were heated at once) to give Light enough for taking of Gun-powder out of the Gun-room of a Ship, or out of a Magazine, without danger of firing the Powder, which would be a means to prevent thoſe ſad accidents, that have but too frequently happened to Ships, eſpecially of War, of which we had very lately a notable inſtance in the River of <hi>Thames.</hi> In proſecution of this Deſign, we took ſome Grains of our Conſiſtent <hi>Phoſphorus,</hi> and having put them into a round Glaſs-Egg, ſomewhat larger than an ordinary Hen Egg, fitted with a ſtem of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable bigneſs, and about two thirds of a Foot long. This being
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:48263:52"/> Hermetically ſealed up, (at leaſt as far as we diſcerned) the Globulous part of it was warily, and by Degrees, warmed at the Fire, and then we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly removed it into a dark place, were the included Matter, not only ſhone by great odds more vividly than before it was heated, but ſome portions of it were brought to an actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al flame, as appeared both by the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diant Splendor of the Burning Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and by the condition of the Smoke, it emitted: And yet more manifeſtly, by the intenſe heat which the flaming part of the Matter (and not the other parts (communicated to that part of the Glaſs, which it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered to; for there the Veſſel was not to be ſo much as touched without inconvenience; and when this flame expired, which it did after no long time, the portion of the lately kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled Matter did no more ſhine or burn as before, but was reduced to the condition of the reſt of the <hi>Noctilu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Matter, together with which it did for a good while retain a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:48263:53"/> degree of Light, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the heat, it had been expos'd to, over and above that Luminouſneſs that ordinarily belonged to it.</p>
                           <p>This Experiment appeared ſo ſtrange, and was ſo delightful to thoſe that had never ſeen it, that partly to gratify the curious, and partly to purſue my own deſign, 'twas reitera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted within the compaſs of a Month or two, between (if I miſtake not) twenty and thirty times, the ſame Matter being ſtill kept in the ſame Veſſel, though by being melted, and in great part ſublim'd by its frequent approaches to the Fire, it was divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into ſeveral parcels. But this made the Experiment ſo much the more pleaſant, in regard that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times (for it was not always) more than one or perhaps than two por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Matter would ſeem to burn at once. This was looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a very new and ſcarce credible thing, that one ſhould be able to bring a Bodie to Burn with an actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al flame, and for no inconſiderable
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:48263:53"/> time, in a Glaſs Hermetically Sealed, and not large neither. But to deal with <hi>Philoſophical</hi> ſincerity, I muſt not conceal from you, that after we had made many Tryals, in the above mentioned Glaſs, there happened a <hi>Phaenomenon,</hi> which gave me ſome ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition, that at that time, it was not actually Sealed: But it did not appear, but that it had been very well Seal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at firſt, and might continue ſo during ſeveral Tryals, for after this ſuſpition we uſed this Glaſs ten or twelve times, or perhaps oftner to make the before recited Experiment, and after all thoſe we could perceive no crack or flaw at all in the ball or ſtem of the Glaſs, and found it diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to get in the point of a ſmall pin into a little hole, which we either found, or, by endeavouring to find one, made at the <hi>Apex.</hi> However, by the things formerly related, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, that our <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter would Burn with leſs vent by great odds, than other fewels known to us, and that a ſmall quantity may be
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:48263:54"/> made to burn and ſhine longer, than one would expect. And we were encouraged by what we ſaw, to hope that if a more conſiderable quantity of Matter, were put into a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſhaped Glaſs, and aſſiſted with other friendly Circumſtances, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if the Luminouſneſs could be a little heightened, it may be rendred fit to be of ſome uſe in Ships, and Magazines of Powder.</p>
                           <p>If I had been furniſhed with ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations, when I firſt made the foregoing Experiment, I would have purſued the Tryal ſomewhat further, by making a pretty quantity of our <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter, burn ſeveral times, in a thin Glaſs-Veſſel, exquiſitely cloſed with <hi>Hermes</hi> his Seal, that, by weighing the Veſſel in exact Scales, both before and after the accenſion of the included <hi>Phoſphorus,</hi> I might find whether any ponderable parts were ſubtile enough to pervade the pores of the Glaſs, and in caſe they were not, I then hoped to diſcover, what change of texture might be made in
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:48263:54"/> the Matter of a bodie, reduced to an actual flame, in a Veſſel, wherein it could not receive the free Air, nor emit any Fumes or exhalations, which would have been to me a very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable Experiment: And perhaps would have prov'd a very inſtructive one too. Since, as I have in another place complain'd, in the <hi>Analyſes,</hi> hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto made by <hi>Chymiſts,</hi> either the body expoſed to the Fire, has not been actually inflamed, which is the caſe of Thoſe diſtill'd in exactly clos'd Veſſels, or elſe there has been ſome commerce betwixt Them, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Air, which may juſtly render it doubtful, whether the bodies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by this <hi>Analyſis</hi> were the ſame both for number, nature, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that would have been produced in Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, exquiſitely cloſed, ſince we ſee that Wood, for Inſtance, burned in a Chimny, affords ſtore of Soot and Aſhes, which are very differing bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies from thoſe that <hi>Chymiſts</hi> obtain from the ſame Wood, Diſtill'd in cloſe Veſſels.</p>
                           <pb n="94" facs="tcp:48263:55"/>
                           <p>But to trouble you no further with what <hi>I would have done,</hi> I ſhall add one Circumſtance, I obſerved, in what <hi>was</hi> done. Namely, That ſometimes there appeared a little Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor in the Glaſs (whether it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of ſome Aqueous Particles, that may be ſuſpected to have lain hid in the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter, or were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the actual deflagration of a part of the Matter) and the reſt of the Matter by the reiterated opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the Fire was turned to a Red Colour, which it yet retains.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div n="14" type="section">
                        <head>
                           <hi>SECT.</hi> XIV.</head>
                        <div n="1" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> I.</head>
                           <p>I Have formerly related, that upon the immerſion of our <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> into Water, it would immediately ceaſe ſhining, and continue without Light, as long as 'twas kept under that Liquor. This gave me a ground to ſuppoſe, that, by the interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Water between the <hi>Noctilu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi>
                              <pb n="95" facs="tcp:48263:55"/> Matter and the Air, the <hi>Phoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus</hi> may be kept unactive, till it be fitted, by an extraordinary agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of its parts, to act with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wonted vigour, when the Air ſhall come to touch it ſuddenly; this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, I ſay, induced me to put two Grains of our <hi>Icy Noctiluca</hi> into a ſmall Glaſs Egg, and pour a pretty quantity of Water on it: In order to the following Experiment, we heated the Liquor well, yet without making it at all boil, and thereby melted the little Fragments of Solid Matter, and made them flow into one Liquid Maſs, that kept it ſelf at the bottom, diſtinct from the Water: This done, we preſently remov'd the Glaſs into a dark place, and pouring out the Water, we obſerv'd, that as ſoon as the Air came to touch the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter, it ſeemed to be kindled into an actual flame, that afforded a very Vivid Light, which ſucceſs pleaſed me the better, becauſe it ſhewed, that a kind of Fire may be kept under Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as long as one pleaſes, without ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:48263:56"/> burning, and yet in a moment, upon the bare removal of the Water, ſhew it ſelf in the form of actual Fire. That our ſhining Subſtance was of this nature appeared manifeſtly by this, That the Water, being poured out ſomewhat too haſtily, carried along with it, which I did not intend it ſhould do, the whole Maſs of the <hi>Nocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucal</hi> Matter, and This<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by its fall into the Silver Cup, that was employ'd to receive the Liquor, was divided into two or three parts, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a more free or full contact of the Air, blaz'd out much more than when they were in the Glaſs, and afforded us a delightful ſpectacle, ſince the flame burned upon the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with much Light and fierceneſs, and a ſtrange deal of Smoke, and it did ever and anon, ſputter with noiſe, like Salt Petre made to burn upon a live Coal. Theſe flames continued the pleaſure we had to ſee them burn upon the water a pretty while, and after their extinction, looking into the Siver Cup, we found divers flakes
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:48263:56"/> of a Reddiſh Matter, (which the <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> would call a <hi>Caput Mortuum</hi>) that lay at the bottom of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and the ſides of the Silver Cup, that were next to that Liquor look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed almoſt as if fine Brick-duſt had been ſtrewed upon them.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> II.</head>
                           <p>Being deſirous to ſee whether, our <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter ſhining through a Coloured Glaſs, the Beams of Light would be ting'd in their paſſage, we took two or three Grains of our Matter, and put it into a Phial, of an almoſt Spherical Figure, capable of holding, by our eſtimate, about twelve Ounces of Water; which Phial was made of fine Glaſs, of a very pleaſant Colour, participating of thoſe that are call'd Orange and Aurora: But the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid Matter, being ſhut up in this Phial, and carried into a dark Room, did not appear through the Glaſs to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably altered in Colour; whch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I imputed partly to the ſmalneſs
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:48263:57"/> of the Fragment of the <hi>Phoſphorus,</hi> in reference to the capacity of the Veſſel, through which it would give no more than a faint Light, I cauſed the Glaſs to be conſiderably heated, and then brought it into the dark Room, I ſtaid for it in, there as ſoon as 'twas come, the included matter ſeem'd to be actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally flaming, and the trajected Beams of Light appeared of an unuſual and glorious Colour, the Light being ſo conſiderable, that it made divers Bodies diſtinctly viſible, at a pretty diſtance from the Glaſs; and we judg'd that by the help of it a Book of a good Print might have been eaſily read; but this Light, which was the greateſt we had, till then, produced with our <hi>Phoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus,</hi> did not laſt long in its vigour, but in a ſhort time gradually decay'd, till it came to little more than the uſual ſplendor of the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="experiment">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> III.</head>
                           <p>I formerly related, that I could not make ſuch an Experiment, as I ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:48263:57"/> tryed with the Oyl of <hi>Cinamon</hi> and the Oyl of <hi>Cloves,</hi> to ſucceed with the Oyl of <hi>Mace.</hi> But now I muſt add, that the little Phial, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Noctilucal</hi> Matter and that Oyl were included, having been ſet aſide as uſeleſs, I afterwards chanced to caſt my Eyes on it, and to have the curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to try, whether or no the unſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Experiment I had made before, were not one of that kind, which in another Paper I have diſcourſed of, under the name of <hi>Contingent ones,</hi> and accordingly there being a ſomewhat dark corner in the Room, I carried the Phial thither, and although it were yet broad day, I unſtopt it there, and was ſomewhat ſurpriz'd to find the included Matter to afford immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately a vigorus Light, which put me afterwards upon repeating the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment at different times, which I did with the like ſucceſs, without being able to determine the cauſe of this odd <hi>Phaenomenon.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="4" type="experiment">
                           <pb n="100" facs="tcp:48263:58"/>
                           <head>
                              <hi>Experiment</hi> IV.</head>
                           <p>One Experiment I ſhall now relate, which, though (becauſe it ſeems, as well as the laſt recited, a contingent one, I forbore to ſet down with the reſt) will perhaps be thought more ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar than any of them.</p>
                           <p>We had in one of our Receivers, that was but ſmall (ſince it was not judged capable of containing a Gallon of Water) a parcel of our Conſiſtent <hi>Noctiluca,</hi> in which my Laborant told me, that he had met with a <hi>Phaenome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> that to him who knew nothing of what is related <hi>Sect.</hi> XIV. <hi>Exper.</hi> 1. was very ſurprizing, and ſeemed to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by chance, ſince he often tryed in vain, to produce it when he pleaſed. This Receiver I took into my cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and pouring out the common Water, with which the ſplendid Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was kept covered to hinder it from ſteaming away, we obſerved no other change, than that, upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of the Water and the contact
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:48263:58"/> of the Air, the <hi>Noctiluca</hi> would imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſhine, and continue to do ſo, till we thought fit to extinguiſh it <hi>pro tempore,</hi> by pouring Water on it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
                           <p>This being done in the Morning, I conſidered the following Night, that this <hi>Receiver</hi> having been kept in the Laboratory, which conſtant and ſometimes vehement Fires made a very warm place, 'twas but fit in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to make the Tryal a fair one, to bring the ſhining Matter to as great a warmth, as it had in the Laboratory, where it exhibited the <hi>Phaenomenon,</hi> I was deſirous to ſee. Having then cauſed the Receiver, with the Water in it, to be held in a hot place, till the Liquor had attained, by our gueſs, a fit degree of Tepidity, we poured out the Water, and within a minute or two after, by our eſtimate, we had the pleaſure to ſee, that the conſiſtent Matter, notwitſtanding the wetneſs that in probability the Water had leſt on it, we obſerv'd I ſay, that This wet Matter, upon the contact of the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:48263:59"/> Air, took Fire of it ſelf, not without noiſe, and burnt with a manifeſt and actual Flame. But our pleaſure was ſomewhat moderated, though the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment was the more aſcertained, by this accident: That, before we could pour in Water to quench the Fire, the violence of the flame had broken the Receiver, which was thick enough, and thrown off a piece above half as broad as the Palm of ones Hand, by which unlucky chance we were hindred from endeavouring to find, as we intended to do, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we could by repeated Tryals di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcover the cauſe of the appearing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingency of this odd <hi>Phaenomenon,</hi> which had far oftner in vain, than ſucceſsfully, been endeavoured to be produced.</p>
                           <p>This Experiment recalls into my memory a notable <hi>Phaenomenon</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to that formerly recited (<hi>Sect.</hi> XI. <hi>Exper.</hi> 2.) about the kindling of our <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> with the Sun-Beams, united by a burning Glaſs: For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, I there mention, that the <hi>Noctilucal</hi>
                              <pb n="103" facs="tcp:48263:59"/> Matter did not burn all away at firſt, but left a kind of <hi>Caput Mortuum,</hi> which lay in the form of a Cake va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly coloured, I ſhall now add, that ſo much Matter could not be left unfired, unleſs ſomething hindered its accenſion; we warily turned over the little Cake, with the point of a ſharp Knife, and then the under part, being I preſumed hot, preſently took Fire upon the contact of the Air, and flamed away, till the Matter was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt totally conſumed.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <head>The Concluſion.</head>
                     <p>AND now I have acquainted you with all the chief things, that I have hitherto been able to try, or obſerve about our <hi>Icy Noctiluca,</hi> or ſolid <hi>Phoſphorus:</hi> And though I have been oblig'd to deliver them without any exact Method, yet perhaps their novelty will ſerve to make them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to you. Light is ſo noble a thing, that the matter, our <hi>Phoſphorus</hi> affords it to reſide in, being endued
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:48263:60"/> with ſome uncommon qualities, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly with a ſtrange and almoſt incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible ſubtilty of parts, I cannot but hope, that, if improvements upon ſuch a Matter were more induſtriouſly attempted, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons better qualified for ſuch a Work, than I (eſpecially in my preſent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances) pretend to be, ſomething would be produced, tending to the diſcovery of the nature, not only of Light, but divers other Bodies, and perhaps alſo, of good uſe to humane life. If ſome unwelcome Circumſtances did not for the preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage me, I would contribute my weak endeavours towards ſuch a deſign. For ſometimes I think a Naturaliſts Pen, ought to be like a Merchants Ship, that comes from time to time into Port to reſt, but not always to ſtay there, but to take in new Lading, and re-fit it ſelf for a new Voyage to the ſame or other parts. In the mean time I recommend this Subject to your ſelf, and thoſe excellent <hi>Virtuoſi,</hi> you hold Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with, whoſe ingenious At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to advance true <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> will have, for their good ſucceſs, the hearty wiſhes of</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your moſt Affectionate, and moſt Humble Servant, <hi>R. B.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:48263:60"/>
                  <p>A CHYMICAL PARADOX, Grounded upon NEW EXPERIMENTS, Making it probable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That Chymical Principles are Tranſmutable: So that, out of One of Them, Others may be Produc'd.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the Honourable <hi>ROBERT BOYLE,</hi> Fellow of the <hi>Royal Society.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. E.</hi> for <hi>B. Tooke,</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1681/2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:48263:61"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:48263:61"/>
                  <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT OF THE PUBLISHER TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>THE Following <hi>PA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RADOX</hi> having been written in or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Year <hi>1680.</hi> was kept in the Author's Hands, that it might come out with the Latin Verſion of his Treatiſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>The Producibleneſs of
<pb facs="tcp:48263:62"/> Chymical Principles,</hi> which is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the Second Edition of His <hi>Sceptical Chymiſt,</hi> printed <hi>1680.</hi> but ſome unluckie Accidents ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pt that Tranſlation from being finiſhed, the Author thought ſit the enſuing Paper ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company his <hi>Icy Noctiluca,</hi> both in <hi>Engliſh</hi> and in <hi>Latin:</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this account, he ſent me not only the Diſcourſe, that now comes forth, but ſome other Papers, containing the Minutes taken from time to time, by his <hi>Laborant,</hi> of what occurr'd in the long Train of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillations, on which the following Reflexions are grounded. For, the Reader, whether Forreign or Domeſtick, may here be pleaſed to be advertiſed, once for all, That as the Author hath been pleaſed
<pb facs="tcp:48263:62"/> to publiſh all his Works in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, for Reaſons beſt known to himſelf; ſo the Province of the Tranſlating them into <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,</hi> hath been undertaken by others: For, indeed, his Aſſiduity and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Attendance on his daily and growing <hi>Experiments,</hi> will not allow him leiſure or opportunity to undertake that Work himſelf; tho otherwiſe if he had a deſire to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh any thing in that Tongue, his Pen can command a ſluent ſtile. This by the by. But I having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the Author both his own Papers, and my Verſion of them, in one Roll, it unfortunately hapned, that before the <hi>Icy Noctiluca</hi> was printed off, there broke out in the Night a great Fire not far from the Author's Lodging, which
<pb facs="tcp:48263:63"/> was ſo threatning, even after the blowing up of ſeveral Houſes to ſtop it, that, as many others were obli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed haſtily to remove their Gods, our Author thought ſit by the ſame way to endeavour to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e his own Manuſcripts; but did it not ſo ſucceſsfully, but that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> yet miſſing; and, among others, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers lately mentioned. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>andin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which, the Importance of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Subje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, and the Nov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lty of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Experiments, prevailed with the Author, to prevent the like miſchance from hapning to what be could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ive concerning th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m) t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> communicate them to the Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, who will, by what I have here related, be enabled to underſtand what he writes at the beginning
<pb facs="tcp:48263:63"/> of that part of the following Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which, becauſe it was written after the Fire above-mentioned, and very long after the reſt, he calls his <hi>Poſtſcript.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:48263:64"/>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:48263:64"/>
                  <head>A CHYMICAL PARADOX.</head>
                  <p>I Adventured many years ago, in the <hi>Sceptical Chymiſt,</hi> and long after in other Papers, to lay down ſome Reaſons of Queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>whether</hi> the Fire be the true and proper Inſtrument of Analyzing mix'd Bodies, and do but <hi>diſſociate</hi> their Principles or Ingredients, without <hi>alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> them or <hi>compounding</hi> them anew. But I ſhall now preſent you a diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that will perhaps make you think the Vulgar opinion of Chymiſts to be leſs fit to be <hi>doubted</hi> of, than <hi>rejected.</hi> The occaſion of making the following Experiments, was afforded me by the complaint of an ingenious Chymiſt, (and great Diſtiller) who told me, that endeavouring to purify an Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Oyl by Rectification, he found
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:48263:65"/> to his diſappointment, that he Diſtill'd it four or five times ſucceſſively, yet it ſtill left ſome Faeces, (but much leſs than at the firſt) though he conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that if he ſhould undergoe the trouble of diſtilling the Liquor, a few times more, it would come over perfectly pure, without leaving any faeculency behind it. But 'twas more congruous to my <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture, that the <hi>Caput Mortuum</hi> he complained of, was not, (at leaſt after the firſt or ſecond Diſtillation,) a more groſs or <hi>Faeculent part</hi> of the Oyl, ſeparated from the more <hi>pure;</hi> but a <hi>new compound</hi> produced, as other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes alſo might be, by the operation of the Fire. This conjecture of mine was favoured by ſome Experiments, I had made many years before, and imparted to ſome inquiſitive men, whereby two diſtill'd Liquors were made, barely by their mutual re-acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to afford great ſtore of an Earthly and very fixed Subſtance. And to the ſame conjecture it was ſuitable, that by obſtinately reitera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:48263:65"/> the Experiment, the action o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Fire upon the parts of the Body, expoſed to it, and their mutual ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and combinations among themſelves, and not improbably too, the material concurrence of Igneous particles, might produce, beſides Earthly faeces, other Bodies not unlike <hi>thoſe</hi> that paſs for the Chymiſts Principles. How far the event pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved agreeable to his <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> will be beſt gathered from the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> themſelves, of the Tryals, which I ſhall proceed to ſet down a ſuccinct account of, as ſoon as I have premiſed, to make way for it, That by an Eſſential Oyl, Chymiſts are wont to mean ſuch a fine Oleagenous Liquor, as to prevent Empyreume and faeculent parts, has been diſtill'd with ſtore of Water in a (<hi>Veſica</hi> or) Limbeck.</p>
                  <p>We took a pound of Eſſential Oyl of Annifeeds, which Liquor (we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made choice of, becauſe 'tis more eaſie to diſcern it, by its ſelf-coagula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting property, not to be ſophiſticated; and having put it into a Glaſs Retort
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:48263:66"/> of a convenient ſize, we cauſed it to be Diſtill'd, (in a Sand Furnace, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of giving a ſtrong Fire) thirty ſix times, in which train of Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the enſuing <hi>Phaenomena</hi> were both congruous to our <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> and in themſelves obſervable.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. As pure as the Eſſential, or, as ſome <hi>Spagyriſts</hi> ſtile them, the Aetheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Oyls of Vegetables are preſum'd to be, and as confidently as Chymiſts pretend they are, the pure Sulphurs or Unctuous principles of the Bodies that afford them; yet, not only the firſt diſtillation left a Subſtance Black, like Pitch, at the bottom of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort, but, at every one of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſtillations, ſuch a Subſtance was either ſeparated or generated.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Though after a Diſtillation or two it ſeemed likely, that this Pitchy Subſtance would be found every time leſs and leſs, which made the perſon, formerly mentioned, tell me, that he ſuppoſed within ten or at moſt twelve Diſtillations, in all, if one ſhould make ſo many this which he lookt upon as
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:48263:66"/> an Earthy recrement would be quite ſeparated, and leave the Oyl a moſt pure and Homogeneous Liquor; yet I that (as I formerly intimated) look'd upon this black ſtuff not as a ſeparated Excrement, but generated Subſtance, cauſed the Diſtillations to be repeated till they had attained thrice that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and not only found that at each time, ſuch a black Subſtance was left; but that now and then a ſubſequent Diſtillation yielded much more of <hi>it</hi> than the precedent had done; which change, from leſs to more, and from more to leſs, was not obſerved only once or twice, but ſeveral times. And though this odd Pitchy Subſtance were towards the latter end found in leſs quantity, than at the beginning, yet the cauſe of that may well be, that the Oyl to be Diſtill'd did ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly from time to time decreaſe in Bulk, partly by reaſon of the receſs of that portion of the Oyl, which could not but be diſſipated and loſt in ſo many Cohobations; and partly, and indeed chiefly, by the loſs of ſo
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:48263:67"/> much Oyl as was tranſmuted into Pitch and other Subſtances.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Oyl appeared in Diſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion more fixed or unapt to riſe than one would have expected from ſo fine and light a Liquor, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially towards the latter end of the Diſtillations, it was often neceſſary to employ a ſcarce credible degree of Fire to elevate all, that was not turned into Pitch.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Liquor did not Diſtill like a pure Principle or Homogeneous Body, as Quickſilver is wont to do, but firſt ſome fine and light Oyl uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally came over, after which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a leſs volatile Oyl with another Subſtance or two, and after that, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſcended in a diſtinct manner.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. For 'tis to be noted that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the forementioned black Earth, there were produced by the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Fire divers other Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, whereof the firſt was a Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriſh Liquor or Phlegm; which, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Oyl had been expoſed to ſome Diſtillations, began to grow very
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:48263:67"/> troubleſome. For being rarified by the heat of the Fire into large bubbles, the Antipathy, or rather Incongruity, between them and the Oyl, occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a kind of conflict, wherein theſe Bubbles did often ſuddenly break, (uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally not without much noiſe) and ſometimes with ſuch violence, as to ſhake and endanger the Retort; which once, by this conteſt, was actually broken; yet not ſo, but that the Liquors and other products of the Fire were ſaved by the watchful La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borant, and ſeaſonably transferred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a new Retort.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Beſides this Phlegm, and the Pitch formerly taken notice of, our operation afforded us from time to time a pretty quantity of a certain Subſtance, which, with ſome not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilful Perſons, paſſed for a Volatile Salt; becauſe it aſcended to the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per part of the Veſſel, and appeared in a dry form, almoſt like ſhort Nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles; and becauſe alſo, it ſeemed to the Laborant, that, like a Salt, it was (part of it at leaſt) diſſoluble in the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:48263:68"/> Spirituous Phlegm, mentioned in the laſt Number. But though at firſt, I inclined to this Opinion, yet having made ſome few Tryals to examin the truth of it, I was, and ſtill am, a little doubtful, whether this ſublim'd Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy deſerve the name of a true Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Salt, though poſſibly there may be a pretty deal of <hi>that</hi> contain'd in it. For I found the lumps of it, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their ſeeming Spongi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to ſink in common Water, and continue at the bottom of it without manifeſtly being diſſolv'd by that Liquor, (as meer Volatile Salts are wont eaſily to be) either in the Cold, or by being kept a while in a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate heat. I found this Subſtance fuſible, like Bees-wax, at the flame of a ſmall Taper, and if a lump of it were kindled thereat, it would burn away, partly with a Yellow flame, and partly with a flame more intenſly Blue, than <hi>That</hi> of rectified Spirit of Wine, but it appeared apt enough to go out of it ſelf.</p>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:48263:68"/>
                  <p>Theſe, and ſome other things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd me to look upon our anoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Sublimate, as a Subſtance, <hi>ſui ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris;</hi> but yet ſuch a one, as I ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be ſomewhat of kin to a <hi>Sal Volatile Oleoſum,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Camphire</hi> ſeems to be. For our Sublimate riſes without ſtrong Fire, and that in a dry form, and is eaſily enough fuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; all which I have obſerved in <hi>Camphire,</hi> as well as in Volatile Salts, and our Sublimate will, like <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire,</hi> diſſolve in a high rectified Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Spirit without at all Colouring the Liquor. And having long ſince found by tryal, that <hi>Camphire</hi> will, though ſlowly, diſſolve in good Oyl of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> and make the Menſtruum look of a Reddiſh Brown; I put ſome of that ſolvent upon our Sublimate, and after having left them ſome hours together, though but in the Cold, the Liquor ſeemed to have diſſolved part of the dry Body, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, by its action upon it, acquired a Brown Colour ſomewhat inclining to Red; and part of this Liquor
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:48263:69"/> being put into a pretty deal of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Water, there ſeemed to Emerge by degrees a dry Body, or <hi>Flores,</hi> which brought into my mind, what I have elſewhere obſerved, when I im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd the ſame method, to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Camphire</hi> out of Oyl of <hi>Vitriol.</hi> But, as I was lately intimating, thoug I think it not improbable, that our <hi>Anomalous Sublimate</hi> may be nearer of kin to a <hi>Sal Volatile Oleoſum,</hi> than to any of the Chymical Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; yet I have not hitherto found the reſemblance betwixt <hi>it</hi> and ſuch a Salt, to be compleat enough to make me <hi>Dogmatical</hi> in referring it to any <hi>Chymical Product,</hi> of a known denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: And therefore, till I be further ſatisfied, I ſhall only add, that this Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Salt, or Oily Sublimate, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever name it may deſerve, was very pretty to look upon, being glittering al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt like ſome fine flowers of <hi>Benzoin;</hi> and of this we had, though it were very light, between two or three Drams.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Beſides all theſe differing Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, our Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds</hi> afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:48263:69"/> us from time to time, a little quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of <hi>Spirit,</hi> as we concluded from two or three Signs; <hi>One,</hi> that it came not over with the Phlegm, and yet would mingle with that Liquor, but not with the Diſtill'd Oyl: And <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> that, as it was more fixed than the Oyl and Phlegm, ſo it roſe latter than they; and not only needed a ſtronger degree of Fire; but, which is chiefly conſiderable, it was uſually obſerved, to come over in white fumes, as many Spirits, that are ſomewhat fixed, are wont to do; which was the more eaſy to be obſerved, becauſe, that being willing to make uſe of the ſame Retort as long as we could, for the greater certainty of the Experiment, and the Pitch being not to be taken out, whilſt 'twas any thing ſoft, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of its cloſe ſticking to the Glaſs, it was thought, to give at the latter end of the Diſtillation, ſo ſtrong a Fire, as, by making the Sand and Retort red hot (or very little leſs hot) would make the Pitch ſo dry and brittle, that it might afterwards be looſened from
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:48263:70"/> the ſides of the Glaſs, and got out in the form of a dry and brittle, though exceeding Black Subſtance. And to the <hi>two</hi> foregoing ſigns I ſhall now add a <hi>third,</hi> that does more clearly evince, that the Subſtance we have been ſpeaking of, was a Spirit: For, though it could not but be very much weakned by being diffuſed through ſo great a quantity of Phlegm, as came over before it, yet its Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſcles were ſo many and vigorous, that when I put them upon the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>crude Coral,</hi> they preſently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to diſſolve it, and the <hi>Phlegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Spirit</hi> did in a trice make a great <hi>Ebullition</hi> with noiſe and bubbles, whether I poured it on the fix'd Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> or the Urinous and Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Salt of <hi>Sal Armoniack.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſucceſs of this Experiment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing anſwerable enough to what I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired and expected from it, allow'd me to make divers reflections on it, and particularly thoſe that follow.</p>
                  <p>And, 1. Our Tryal argues, that a Subſtance, that is looked upon by
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:48263:70"/> Chymiſts as a homogeneous Body, and which paſſes for one of their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, (for that is the caſe of our Eſſential Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds</hi>) may yet be of ſuch a nature, that barely by the further action of the Fire, it may be made to afford a very conſiderable proportion of a Subſtance excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly different from that which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded it. For in our Experiment, we obtained a <hi>Caput Mortuum,</hi> whoſe qualities were quite other, than <hi>thoſe</hi> of Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds;</hi> ſince it was opa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous, black, dry, very difficultly fuſible, and fixt, in ſo ſtrong a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Fire, as made the Retort that contained it, and the Sand about it red hot. This Subſtance would lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſolved in a highly Rectified Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Spirit, into which Oyl of <hi>Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds</hi> would readily have diffuſed it ſelf (if they had been a litte ſhaken together) without the help of heat. And though we made the Liquor actually boyle a pretty while, yet moſt of the <hi>Caput Mortuum</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued a black Subſtance, only it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coloured
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:48263:71"/> the Menſtruum, which lookt as if it had rather extracted a Tincture, than made a ſolution properly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. And of this black and Pitch-like <hi>Caput Mortuum,</hi> we had at the end of our Diſtillations, when we weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſeveral parcels altogether, not much leſs (which you may juſtly think ſtrange) than half the weight of the whole Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds;</hi> this black ſtuff amounting to a pretty deal more than ſeven Ounces. And from hence we may collect, that the <hi>Analyſis,</hi> wont to he acquieſced in by vulgar Chymiſts; is as yet, but an indetermined thing, ſince they have not declared (nor perhaps thought of any ſuch thing) what number of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillations, (whether one or more, or if more then one, how many,) ſhall be made the ſtandard, by which we are to conclude, that a Subſtance, obtained by Diſtillation, is a Chymical Principle.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It may be alſo inferred from ſome <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of our Experiment, that the Fire, as 'tis wont to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd, is not, as Chymiſts pretend it
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:48263:71"/> to be, the true and genuine Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Analyſis</hi> of Bodies, ſince it does not, as they preſume it does, bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extricate and ſeparate the ſeveral ſimilar Subſtances, that, though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed and diſguiſed by commixtures with each other, were pre-exiſtent (in the ſame forms wherein they afterwards appear) in the Body ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to its operation. For in our caſe the Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds</hi> is, according to the Chymiſts eſtimate, the <hi>Sulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reous Principle</hi> of the Concrete; and therefore has not any other Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, eſpecially in any conſiderable quantity, contained in it. And yet, by the bare action of the Fire, this Oyl, which they acknowledge to be a ſimilar Body, is brought to afford three or four other Subſtances, of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring natures from one another.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. From the two foregoing Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations we may likewiſe deduce, That the Fire, at leaſt in divers caſes, may not only <hi>ſeparate,</hi> but variouſly <hi>compound</hi> and <hi>alter,</hi> the parts of a Body expoſed to its action; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:48263:72"/> give conſidering men cauſe to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, that divers Subſtances, that are preſumed to be only <hi>Extricated</hi> or <hi>Extracted</hi> by the operation of the Fire, may be really produced by it.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Agreeably to which ſuſpicion, it happens unluckily enough for the Chymical <hi>Hypotheſis;</hi> that in our Experiment, the Subſtances that were obtained, were, a fixt and Earthy Powder, a not inconſiderable portion of Phlegm, a Spirituous Liquor, and a dry Sublimate, a-kin to a <hi>Volatile Salt:</hi> And theſe, though they all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from a Body, that, according to the Chymiſts <hi>ſhould</hi> not, and indeed, for ought appears, <hi>did</hi> not actually contain any of them before, did yet ſo reſemble in qualities the Earths, Phlegm, and Spirit, that Chymiſts ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain by Diſtillation from thoſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, they look upon as perfectly mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and compounded, that if they are not the ſame, they have divers qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, ſo like <hi>thoſe,</hi> that entitle what is afforded by confeſſedly mix'd Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to the name of Phlegm or Salt,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:48263:72"/> or ſome other Primordial Ingredient, that the Earth for inſtance, or the <hi>(acid)</hi> Spirit obtain'd in our Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment, are far leſs differing from the Earth of Blood, or the Spirit of <hi>Amber,</hi> than theſe are from the Earth and Salt of throughly Calcined <hi>Hartshorn.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. 'Twill ſcarce be neceſſary to draw ſo obvious a Corollary from what has been already deliverd, as this; That 'tis poſſible, that Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Principles (or at leaſt ſuch Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as a Vulgar Chymiſt, not knowing from what Body they were obtain'd, would look upon, as ſuch) may be made of another.</p>
                  <p>But though I ſhall not enlarge on this <hi>Corollary,</hi> it will not be amiſs to make one conſiderable Obſervation, that belongs to it. Namely, that <hi>Acid</hi> and <hi>Aqueous</hi> Subſtances, how differing ſoever each of them is from a pure Oyl, may be produced from it, by the action of the Fire. For I found by Tryal, that in that Liquor which the Laborant took for the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:48263:73"/> Phlegm of Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds,</hi> there was ſuch ſtore of Acid parts, that (as was above recited) they would readily diſſolve powdered <hi>Coral,</hi> though crude, even in the cold; and would make a great conflict with Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> and with that of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine,</hi> as ſoon as the Liquor was put upon it. But yet the greateſt part of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor by far, ſeemed to be of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queous nature, which a Chymiſt would call Phlegm; which is a Body that will not mingle with Oyl, and is otherwiſe exceedingly different from Oyl, eſpecially an Eſſential one, (ſuch of that of <hi>Anniſeeds,</hi>) whoſe purity makes it it totally inflamable. And the quantity of the whole Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, conſiſting of Acid and Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick parts, was far from being inconſiderable, amounting to about two Ounces and three quarters. It may alſo be worth while to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, as another thing belonging to our <hi>Corollary,</hi> that the Truth, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in it, allows us to queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be neceſſary to ſuppoſe with
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:48263:73"/> the Chymiſts, that Nature has been oblig'd to make proviſion of great quantities of <hi>Primordial</hi> and <hi>Simple</hi> Bodies, and that ſhe is ſolicitous to mix them all together, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of a Body, capable of affording by the <hi>Analyſis</hi> or ſeparatory Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Fire, Salt, Spirit, Sulphur, Phlegm and Earth: I will not hence univerſally infer, that there are no ſuch Subſtances, one or more to be found, in any of thoſe Bodies that are called perfectly mixed, antecedently to their being expoſed to the Fire. But this, I think, will follow from what has been delivered, that the pre-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of ſuch Subſtances muſt be made out by ſome other way, than the bare operation of the Fire; and that the grand Chymical ſuppoſition will not hold in all Bodies, that <hi>what ſimilar Body ſoever is obtain'd by the operation of the Fire from a Concrete, committed to Diſtillation,</hi> was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and actually pre-exiſtent in it.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. And laſtly, our Experiment af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords us a conſiderable Argument in
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:48263:74"/> favour of that part of the Corpuſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, or Mechanical <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> that teaches, inanimate Bodies to differ from one another, but in the bigneſs, ſhape, motion, contexture, and in a word, the Mechanical affections, of the minute parts they conſiſt of. For in our Experiment, we ſee that Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds,</hi> which is not only an uniform or ſimilar Body, as to ſenſe, but is judged <hi>ſo</hi> by Chymiſts, upon an <hi>Analyſis</hi> of the concrete that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded it, is, by having its parts va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly agitated, ſhak'd, and rubbed againſt one another, and in differing manners broken, aſſociated, and ranged, tranſmuted into four Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of ſuch differing natures and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, as the Chymiſts principles and Elements are known to be. And this without the help of any true Seed or plaſtick Principle, by the bare operation of the Fire, which <hi>Helmont</hi> calls <hi>the Artificial death of things,</hi> and <hi>the deſtroyer of Seminali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> And this is the more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, becauſe, whereas the Ancient
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:48263:74"/> 
                     <hi>Corpuſcularian Philoſophers</hi> aſſigned three general ways whereby Bodies may be produced; namely, by the <hi>addition</hi> of new parts, the <hi>dividing,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>taking away</hi> a portion of the former, and the <hi>Tranſpoſition</hi> of the conſtituent parts, in our Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the whole work ſeems to be performed only by what they would have called <hi>Tranſpoſition,</hi> and that guided but by ſo ſimple, impetuous, and unruly an Agent, as the Fire. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be ſaid, that divers igneous particles, that penetrated the Glaſs Retort, did ſubſtantially aſſociate themſelves with ſome parts of the Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds,</hi> and concur with them to compoſe the Pitch-like <hi>Caput Mortuum;</hi> which they will perhaps ſay, that (whatever others may do) I ought to allow as a poſſible thing; after what I have elſewhere written, purpoſely to ſhew, that ſuch a pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration of the Pores of Glaſs, by the Atoms of Fire is not impoſſible. But the Experiment, I have delivered, of the Ponderability of Flame, prove only
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:48263:75"/> that ſome of its Particles may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine with heavy Bodies, and fix'd in the degree of Fire I expoſed them to; my Tryals having been made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Tin and Lead. And it will not perhaps be thought likely, that Igne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Atoms ſhould, by their combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the Particles of an inflama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Oyl, produce an Aqueous Liquor, and that in great quantity; as we lately noted of the <hi>Acid Phlegm</hi> of <hi>Anniſeeds,</hi> amounting to two ounces and almoſt ſix Drams.</p>
                  <p>Upon the whole Matter, the <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena,</hi> obſervable in our Experiment upon Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds,</hi> ſeem very congruous to the Mechanical <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis,</hi> and very unfavourable to <hi>That</hi> of the Chymiſts. For, whether the Fire be ſuppoſed to have Acted meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as an Agent, or Efficient Cauſe, or to have alſo concurred as a Material one; it appears, that by changes of Texture, without the Addition of any viſible Parts, or of any Seed, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies very differing in Colour, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, Fixity, and divers other
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:48263:75"/> Qualities, may be produced from a Body, not only homogeneous, as to ſenſe, but pure enough to paſs for a Chymical Principle. And, though the ſuſpicion lately propoſed, ſhould be allowed to be Probable, as to the other Products, as well as to the black Subſtance; yet ſtill our Proceſs upon the Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds</hi> would afford conſiderable Corollaries againſt the Chymical Doctrine, I call in queſtion. For, 1. The Objection we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, will give wary men juſt ground to ſuſpect, that in ordinary Chymical Diſtillations the Fire is not always to be looked upon as a meer Inſtrument of <hi>Analyſis;</hi> but may in many, if not in moſt caſes, be alſo a material Cauſe of the ſuppoſed Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, produced by its means; which is quite contrary to the Received Doctrine of the Vulgar Spagyriſts, (who are thoſe, I now diſpute with.) But, not to inſiſt on this Remark, I think our proceſs upon Oyl of <hi>Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds,</hi> will not ſerve to prove the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox propoſed at the beginning of this
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:48263:76"/> Paper; ſince, treating of Ingredients Chymically obtainable, I may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to ſpeak of them in the uſual ſenſe of Chymiſts, who ſuppoſe the different Subſtances, obtained from a Body committed to Diſtillation, to be the <hi>Hypoſtatical</hi> Principles, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ingredients of it, without ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Fire to do any more than extricate or diſentangle them from one another. So that, <hi>Secondly,</hi> (to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude at laſt this long Paragraph) our Experiment ſeems to prove the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of <hi>other</hi> Chymical Principles out of <hi>one,</hi> as validly as <hi>their</hi> Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments prove, that ſuch Principles are obtained from the Bodies, they call Mix'd. For, whereas the force of the lately propoſed ſurmiſe or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, lies in this, that the Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Igneous Particles hinders the different Subſtances, that our Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds</hi> afforded us, from being uncompounded Bodies, and therefore from being true Principles, they may for all this have as good right to the Title of Principles, as moſt of theſe
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:48263:76"/> they will have us take for ſuch: Since the Atoms of the Fire, may every whit as reaſonably be ſuppoſed, to Aſſociate themſelves variouſly with the Corpuſcles of a Mixt Body, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Diſtillation, as with thoſe of Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds,</hi> and ſo their ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Principles will, no more than ours, be free from Compoſition. Nay the advantage in the Compariſon, lyes on our ſide, ſince the different Subſtances, that Chymiſts are wont to obtain from a mixt Body, may be Compounded, not only with Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Particles, but with the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Ingredients of the ſame Body; ſince this in their <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> is a mixt Body; whereas Eſſential Oyl of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſeeds</hi> is by them granted to be a Simple one: And therefore each of its Productions, is compounded with no Extraneous Subſtance, ſave the Corpuſcles of the Fire.</p>
                  <p>When I had framed the Conjecture, <hi>That from a Chymical Principle, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral differing Bodies might be obtained
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:48263:77"/> by the meer operation of the Fire;</hi> I thought fit to endeavour the Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of it, by making Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon other Diſtill'd Oyles, (for thoſe made by expreſſion, are by Chymiſts themſelves, own'd to be Compounded Bodies,) of Natures dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, both from the Oyl of <hi>Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds,</hi> and from one another. And accordingly, whilſt our Proceſs with this Oyl, which the Chymiſts call Eſſential, and which was drawn from a Vegetable Seed, was carrying on, I took care to have Diſtill'd in the ſame Furnace, <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Turpentine;</hi> which, though drawn from a Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Subſtance differs very much from Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds,</hi> as alſo <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Amber;</hi> which, according to Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, belongs to the Mineral King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: And laſtly, <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Harts-horn,</hi> afforded by a Subject, which (to ſpeak in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir Phraſe) belongs to the Animal Kingdom.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:48263:77"/>
                  <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>THeſe Oyls were committed to the ſame Laborant, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged the lately mentioned Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds;</hi> and he accordingly kept a kind of Journal of the number of Rectifications, the Quantities of Pitchy Matter from time to time afforded by them, and divers other <hi>Phaenomena,</hi> or Circumſtances, that occurr'd in ſo tedious a Proſecution, as I thought Experiments of ſuch moment de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. But, the Papers, containing the Minutes of theſe things, having been unhappily loſt, with divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by occaſion of a great Fire, that obliged me after midnight to make a haſty and very diſorderly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move of my Writings, I could never ſince retrieve the Particulars. And therefore I muſt content my ſelf, to ſet down as much of the Tryals
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:48263:78"/> (which I hope will comprize the moſt ſubſtantial part of them) as by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining my own Memory and the Laborants, and by ſome few other helps, I am able to collect: As ſoon as I have given here one Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement, becauſe I think it was omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in the Papers, whence the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going part of this writing, was Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. The Advertiſement is this; that as well in the precedent, as in the ſubſequent part of this Diſcourſe, I do not take <hi>Chymical Principles</hi> in the ſtricteſt ſenſe of that Term, wherein it is confin'd to Salt, Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, and Mercury; but in the lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger acception, wherein the Learned Doctor <hi>Willis,</hi> and divers other Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts (that are not all his <hi>Juniors</hi>) imploy it, when they comprize un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, two Elementary Bodies; as they do when they conſtitute five Principles, (which perhaps might be more clearly call'd <hi>Similar Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents;</hi>) in which number they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize Phlegm and Earth, which other Chymiſts, as well as the <hi>Ariſtotelians</hi>
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:48263:78"/> would call Elements, (of the Body that affords them.) Taking then in this whole Writing, the word <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> in the larger ſenſe above de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared (congruouſly whereunto I uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally call them the <hi>Chymical Principles</hi> indefinitely, not the <hi>Hypoſtatical Principles,</hi> which are accounted but three;) I proceed to the particular Obſervations and Reflections I was going to begin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Then it plainly appears, that two of the three lately mentioned Oyls, namely, the Oyl of <hi>Turpentine,</hi> and the Oyl of <hi>Amber,</hi> and therefore very probably the third alſo, (my deſign being the ſame in all three) were Diſtill'd at leaſt fifty times; for I intended not to ſtop ſhort of that number. And by an Inſcription upon one of the Phials, I found that the Oyl, which the contain'd Liquor was drawn from, had been Diſtill'd one and fifty times: which number exceeds by fifteen, <hi>that</hi> of the Diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations formerly mentioned to have
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:48263:79"/> been made of the Oyl of <hi>Annni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Each of the three other Oyles, (<hi>viz.</hi> that of <hi>Harts horn,</hi> that of <hi>Turpentine,</hi> and that of <hi>Amber,</hi>) did leave from time to time, in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the Retorts, whence they were drawn off, a not inconſiderable quantity of Black Faeces, much like thoſe, that were left by the Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds,</hi> and which I have formerly call'd a Pitchy Subſtance: I found in a Superſcrib'd Paper, ſome quantity of this ſtuff left by the Oyl of <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine,</hi> and, though I am not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, whether it were all the ſtuff of this kind that was afforded by the pound of Oyl we employed, yet it amounted to above two Ounces and five Drams: And if I much miſtake not, the other two Oyls did each of them afford a conſiderable quantity of Black Terreſtrial Matter, though the hee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ul Laborant obſerved, that the Oyl of <hi>Harts-horn</hi> did ſooner leave oft yielding copious Faeces (as I often in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eper call them, to comply
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:48263:79"/> with the Chymiſts Terms, though I aſſent not to their Notion) than the Oyl of <hi>Turpentine,</hi> or that of <hi>Amber.</hi> But if neither of the two afforded any more, than did the Oyl of <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine,</hi> I look upon it as a remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thing, that the Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds,</hi> which is a fine Eſſential Oyl, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd in a Veſica or Limbeck, ſhould yield above twice more of Earthy Matter, than either of the three other Oyles, that were Diſtill'd but in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torts.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Of the Colour of the Rectified Oyl of <hi>Harts-horn</hi> I can ſay little, having unluckily loſt the Liquor it ſelf; but the Oyl of <hi>Amber,</hi> after the one and fiftieth Diſtillation, was indeed very clear, but yet of an <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> Colour, that was far from pale: And the Oyl of <hi>Turpentine,</hi> that is uſually after one Rectification a clear and Colourleſs Liquor, after fifty Diſtillations, appeared almoſt Red.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:48263:80"/>4. But <hi>that</hi> is much more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, which I obſerved in the quantities of the different Liquors, afforded by the long ſeries of our Diſtillations, for at the end of the proceſs, the remaining Oyl of <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine,</hi> for inſtance, did not appear to my Eyes to be conſiderably, if at all, Superiour in bulk to another Liquor, that came over with it in Diſtillation, and was not true Oyl, for it would readily enough mix with Water, but keep it ſelf in a Maſs diſtinct from the Oyl, and weighed above three Ounces and three quarters.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. This oddly produc'd Liquor, I looked upon as compounded of Spirit and of Phlegm: For though the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter did ſo much exceed the other in quantity, that in an expert Chymiſts Opinion, the whole Liquor paſſed for Phlegm; yet, I not only judged ſome parts of it to be Spirits, but found them to be of an <hi>Acid</hi> nature too; ſince, beſides what the taſt made
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:48263:80"/> me ſuſpect, I found that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded Liquor would readily e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough begin to Corrode beaten <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> even in the cold, and ſome of it being poured upon good Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> preſently made with it a Conflict and Ebullition, not without a hiſſing noiſe and a multitude of Bubbles. So likewiſe the Spirituous Phlegm of <hi>Amber</hi> made a conflict with Salt of Tartar, and diſſolved crude Coral, as other weak. <hi>Acid</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are alſo wont to do. This Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor of <hi>Amber</hi> was not pale, as the Phlegmatick Spirit of Oyl of <hi>Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds,</hi> was; and <hi>that</hi> lately mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to have been obtained from Oyl of <hi>Turpentine</hi> was high Coloured, being of a browniſh Red.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. I forgot to take notice in due place (and therefore do it in this) that, among other Tryals made to diſcover, that the Spirits afforded by our Oyls were really Acid, we put two ounces of the Spirituous Phlegm of Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds</hi> (that being the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:48263:81"/> mildeſt Oyl) upon ſome <hi>Minium;</hi> and, having digeſted them a while together, found the Liquor turn'd ſweet, and fit (as we judged) to make <hi>Saccharum Saturni:</hi> And this Liquor (after Filtration through Cap paper) being gently abſtracted, left in the bottom of the Retort, a thick Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney like Subſtance, from which (the Diſtillation being continued in the ſame Retort, but with a much ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or heat) there came over ſome Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, which being in too little quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity to be Rectified, we could not free it from its Phlegm, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did not find it Inflammable; as I gueſſed the Spirituous part would have been after Rectification, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the Liquor was exceeding like the <hi>Spiritus Ardens Saturni,</hi> I have elſewhere deſcribed in its peculiar, and very penetrating taſte and ſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. It may not he unfit to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of in this place, that, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving lighted on two Phials, that I
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:48263:81"/> long knew not what was become of, one of which contained ſome of the Oyl of <hi>Turpentine,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome of the Oyl of <hi>Amber,</hi> that I formerly mentioned to have been each of them Diſtill'd at leaſt 50 times; I thought fit to try, whether after theſe Liquors had been laid by about a year and half, or longer, they, would after having had ſo long a time to defecate themſelves in, yield ſtill ſuch a black Subſtance, as has been oftentimes mentioned; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, to ſatisfie my ſelf, cauſed each of theſe Liquors to be again Diſtill'd in a Retort, it left behind it a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quantity of a black and ſhining Subſtance, than could well have been expected.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. It may ſeem very odd in it ſelf, and may much ſerve to confirm, what I have elſewhere delivered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Mechanical Origin of Fixity, as alſo of the Qualities oppoſite to Fuſibleneſs and to Fluidity; that, ſo Volatile and thin a Liquor, as a Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:48263:82"/> and Rectified Oyl, ſhould by the bare operation of the Fire, be brought to yield a great quantity of what looks ſo like Terreſtrial faeces, as our Pitchy <hi>Capita Mortua</hi> did. But this reflection will, I preſume, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear the better grounded, if I add the ſucceſs of one Tryal (among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) that I made, to examine the Terreſtrial Nature of the black Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, I am ſpeaking of: For, although many Bodies that will not aſcend, or be diſſipated in cloſe Veſſels, will eaſily be driven away in open ones; yet having put one ounce of the <hi>Caput Mortuum</hi> of the Oyl of <hi>Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds,</hi> and as much of <hi>that</hi> afforded by Oyl of <hi>Turpentine,</hi> each of them into a diſtinct Crucible, and kept them three hours and a half, or near four hours, in ſuch a heat, as made the Veſſels all the while red hot; though we kept not the Crucibles cloſely covered, but only looſly to keep out the Aſhes, yet we found, when the Veſſels were removed from the Fire, that the contain'd Bodies
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:48263:82"/> had not at all been brought to fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, only <hi>that</hi> from the Oyl of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſeeds</hi> was in part ſomewhat caked together: And notwithſtanding, all the heat, they had been expoſed to, the Pitchy Subſtance of the Oyl of <hi>Turpentine,</hi> retain'd not far from three quarters of its firſt weight; and the <hi>Caput Mortuum</hi> of Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds</hi> loſt about eighteen grains leſs than <hi>that.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. After this we alſo endeavoured to diſcover, whether our Pitchy Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances would afford any Fixt or Alcaliſate Salt, as the <hi>Capita Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua</hi> of moſt Bodies belonging to the Vegetable Kingdom, are wont to do. But <hi>though</hi> we kept an Ounce a-piece of the black Subſtances, left by the Oyl of <hi>Anniſeeds</hi> and that of <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine,</hi> for nine or ten hours, red hot in the Crucibles; yet we found indeed the Bodies very much dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in quantity, but they did not appear at all Calcin'd.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Into a couple of Ounces of this laſt named Liquor, we put by
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:48263:83"/> little and little, of much of dry Salt of <hi>Tartar</hi> as it would work upon, as an <hi>Acid,</hi> or (if you pleaſe) till there would no longer be any viſible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict excited by adding more Salt. The Acid being thus mortified or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated, I intended to draw off all the reſt of the Liquor, and to try with the Phlegm drawn off, whether by cohobating it very ſlowly in a new Glaſs-head and Body, I could not make a farther tranſmutation of the Terebinthinate Oyl, and change, at leaſt, part of this Aqueous Phlegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Liquor into a whitiſh Earth. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the poſſibility of which Tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and of ſome others alſo, I might here ſubjoyn an account, if, ſince the lately mentioned Fire, I could have found a ſhort diſcourſe, I wrote, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and examine this grand Phyſico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chymical Probleme, <hi>Whether we ought to admit any other Elements or Hypoſtatical Principles at all, even ſo much as one of the Bodies that are commonly called, mixt:</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:48263:83"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE first Advertiſement,</hi> page 5. line 18. dele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>very. p. 22. l. 5. read <hi>Immerſed.</hi> p. 34. l. 5. r. <hi>Spe-ctators.</hi> p. 40. l. 16. 1. <hi>Operation.</hi> p. 125. l. 22. r. <hi>Little.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
